Let's talk about the types of things that could go wrong when
you're writing a C# application. There are two general categories of errors.
The first type of error, sometimes the easiest type of error to fix, is when you have an error that will not
allow the C# compiler to compile your code. And these can be easy problems to fix because Visual Studio can
show you little red squigglies when you're missing something like a semicolon or if you're missing something
like a curly brace. And perhaps I have an error like this where I'm missing a curly brace inside of a source
code file that I don't even have open and I cannot see the red squigglies.
In that case I might think I'm okay and try to build the solution, but I will get an error list that shows
me output from the C# compiler. And this output is saying that there is a curly brace expected,
a closing curly brace somewhere. Any time this error list window is open I can double-click on a line inside
of the error list, and Visual Studio will open the file that has the error and put the cursor on the position
where the C# compiler thinks the error is. And we looked at this scenario earlier in the module.
Some errors the C# compiler can be very specific and say you are missing a semicolon at this exact location.
In this case, it's just telling me I'm missing a curly brace. It's not really sure where that curly brace
should be, but it does know that the count of curly braces doesn't add up.
There are three opening curly braces, but only two closing curly braces.
If I just type a curly brace down here at the bottom of the file, you'll see that Visual Studio is smart
enough to say, oh this is working now. It reformates my code, puts all the curly braces in the right
position, and I should now be back to having a working application.
So any time the Error List window opens up, just double-click on an error in this table of errors,
and Visual Studio will take you to the location where you can start to look around and see what needs to be fixed up.
The other type of error that you can commonly encounter when writing a C# application is a runtime error.
Let me show you an example of what one would like. Let me build this solution again just to make sure we
are up-to-date, and I'm going to come out and run this solution Hello without passing any parameters.
That means the argument's parameter, the string array that is passed into Main, will be empty.
There are no arguments available. So when I run the program, all sorts of catastrophic error messages pop up.
I can see in the command line window that there was an Unhandled Exception.
We'll be talking more about exceptions in this course, how to both generate exceptions when your application
logic detects something has gone wrong, as well as handling exceptions at runtime so that they don't crash your program.
But here we have a program that doesn't handle any exceptions. That means an error occurred inside the
application, and the runtime, the CLR, is going to shut down the application so that it cannot continue.
It's usually not a good idea to allow a program to continue executing when it has some sort of fatal exception.
Windows has detected that something has gone wrong also, so it pops up this message box, but let me dismiss
this and talk to you a little bit about the debugger. So when you have runtime errors inside of your
application, sometimes you need to do a deep investigation of what is actually happening inside of your
application, and that's when the debugger is useful. The debugger allows me to step through line-by-line
all of the code inside of my application, and inspect variables, and inspect the environment, and try to
figure out where the logic has gone wrong. When you use the debugger, it's very useful to set breakpoints
inside of your application. Breakpoints allow you to stop the application right on a specific line of code,
and then you can start inspecting the environment. To set a breakpoint, just come over out here on the left
hand side of the editor window, this grey strip that I have here, and I can click here, and now I have a red dot.
That is how Visual Studio tells me that I have set a breakpoint on this line.
And now I can come into the Debug menu, and this time instead of Starting Without Debugging I'm going to
Start With Debugging. I could also just press F5. And Visual Studio is going to launch the application,
and it's going to stop execution right on this line of code. Down here in the Windows menu, I can see the application running.
It hasn't produced any output as of yet because we've stopped the program before it got to the WriteLine statement.
And inside of Visual Studio I've had all sort of windows open up.
I'm just going to shut down a few that I don't really need, and I'll show you just a couple of things.
First of all, by default, you should have an Autos window that pops up.
This Autos window will show you some of the variables that are available in the current context where you're debugging.
Right now the only real variable I have is the parameter args, and I can see the value for this is string with
a 0 inside of the square brackets. That's the debuggers way of telling me that args is a string array,
and it's a string array of length 0. That means there are no arguments inside.
I could also do that by hovering the mouse over args. So anything in a C# application that is holding data,
you could put your mouse over this symbol and get this little popup window that shows you what's inside of a
particular variable or data structure. And once you have stopped execution at a breakpoint and you've
inspected some things, you might want to resume the application running.
There are a couple of ways to do that. I can us the F10 and F11 keys to step through my program,
that is step line-by-line. If I'm inside of a method that's calling into another method, F11 will Step Into
the lines of code inside that other method. If I just want the debugger to execute that method and then give
me back control when that method has finished executing, I can use this Step Over command.
And if I think everything is going to work and I just want to continue with the application running,
I can just press F5, and the application will execute until it hits another breakpoint.
Let's try the Step Over command, which is F10, and I can see that this little yellow arrow has advanced one line.
You can think of that yellow arrow as an instruction pointer. It's showing you the current instruction or
the current line of code that's going to be executed. And now I'll just use the shortcut key, F10, to try to
step over this line of code, and this is the line of code that's generating the exception.
And now since I'm in the debugger, Visual Studio is going to halt execution there and pop up a dialogue that
will tell me I'm getting an IndexOutofRangeException. So that is something that you get when you try to
index into an array and you try to grab an element that doesn't exist.
So this code is using args sub 0, it's trying to get to the first element of the array,
but unfortunately args, as we saw before, is a completely empty array so there is no first element,
and that's an error condition that in this scenario is going to force my program to crash.
Something has gone wrong, and the CLR won't allow my program to continue executing.
So let's go into the Debug menu and Stop Debugging. Now one question you may have is how can I pass in some
arguments when I'm running from this Debug menu? It's very easy to do when I'm running from the command line.
I can just type Hello Scott or Hello Joy, but what about when I'm running with the debugger?
To do that, I'm going to go and click on the project Hello. In fact, I'm going to right-click on that project.
Pretty much everything in Visual Studio you can right-click on to get a context menu, and in this case what
I want to do is open up the Properties for this project. This is going to open up a window that shows me all
sorts of configuration and build-related settings for my application, what's the target framework,
what's the name of the executable it's going to produce. There are lots and lots of settings inside of here,
but I just want to, for now, focus on the Debug settings. And in the Debug settings you can see that there
are Start Options where I can specify command line arguments that I want past to this program when I'm
running with the debugger. So let's pass in Scott, and I'll close this window, and now let me press F5 to
run with the debugger. We're going to stop on our breakpoint again.
This time I can see that args is a string array with a length of one, so there's something inside of args.
I can expand this and see that the first element inside of args is Scott.
I can also mouse over args and do the same thing here. And if I press F10 a couple times, I can see that I
stepped over two lines of code, and I should be able to see Hello Scott.
If I come out here to the running program, I can see that it produced the right output.
So let me just press F5 to continue running, and the program will exit.