Now that I've Visual Studio on my machine, I've also installed the .NET Framework because the .NET Framework
is part of the Visual Studio installation. When we write our applications in C# with Visual Studio,
our applications run on top of the .NET Framework, and then our applications can take advantage of services
and programming interfaces that the framework provides. These programming interfaces include the ability
to save information into a database, the ability to read information from an XML file, as well as
cryptography, configuration, network communications, and all the basic core features that nearly every
application needs, and that means you can use C# to build business applications, to build games,
web applications, and apps that run on different types of phones and mobile devices.
We commonly think of the .NET Framework as consisting of two distinct pieces.
First there is the Common Language Runtime, or the CLR, and there's also the Framework Class Library, or the FCL.
Let's talk about these two pieces in more detail.