In various parts of the course, I'll talk about the Common Language Runtime, the CLR, so it's important to
note that the CLR is an execution environment for .NET applications, and that includes applications written in C#.
It is the CLR that is responsible for bringing your application to life and managing it while it executes,
and it's also the CLR's job to tear down your application when it's finished executing or if it has an unrecoverable error.
And here some of the services that the CLR provides when it's managing your application.
One is memory management. The CLR is actively tracking all of the memory that your program uses to do work,
and it knows when your program is finished with memory, so it will clean things up and allow your program
to continue to have enough memory as it runs. The CLR also virtualizes your execution environment,
so for the most part you do not need to worry about what version of the operating system that your
application is executing on, you don't need to worry about the specific CPU that is installed on the machine,
whether that CPU is 32-bit or 64-bit, or how many cores are present, or what instruction set is available.
The CLR will take care of all those things and make sure that your application will execute correctly.
The CLR was also designed to support multiple languages. You can write programs in C#, but you can also write
.NET programs in Visual Basic or F#. In fact, there are many different languages you can use to write .NET
applications, and all those applications will be managed by the same CLR.
The CLR is available for every version of Windows since Windows XP.
There's also a CLR for mobile phones like Windows Phone 8 and a new version of the CLR, the CoreCLR,
will even run on non-Windows machines, like MacBook's running OS X and Linux machines.
For the most part, you don't care which operating system you are on.
Certainly what we will cover in this course will be code that can run anywhere; although, there's always an
option to use an operating-specific feature that would tie your code to a specific platform.
But, as I said, we'll focus on the features of C# and the .NET Framework Class Library that will work anywhere.
And speaking of the Framework Class Library, let me give you a quick overview of the FCL.