While the CLR works in the background to manage your application while it is running, it is the Framework
Class Library of .NET that you will interact with on a day-to-day basis because it's the FCL that contains
reusable software that you use to build applications. It provides you all the functionality to do useful
work like use regular expressions and read and write data from a disk.
You will also hear people refer to the BCL, or Base Case Library, which technically is a subset of the FCL.
It's contained inside the FCL, but it's a subset so it doesn't contain quiet as many features, but it does
work everywhere, and that's what we'll be using for this course, the subset that works everywhere.
But chances are when you start building your own applications you'll be using pieces of the more expansive
Framework Class Library because it is the Framework Class Library that includes software to help you write
desktop applications and web applications and web services and apps.
The FCL is so large and so varied that it is rare for one person to know all the ins and outs of the entire library.
Typically you're going to focus on just a couple areas of the FCL and master those.
Like you might become a master of ASP.NET to build web applications because that's what your business requires.
ASP.NET is just one part of this .NET Framework. And now that we know that we're using C# on top of .NET,
and .NET gives us the CLR to run our applications and the Framework Class Library to give us software
components to build on, let's make this all a little more concrete by writing our first C# program.