C# is one of the languages that you can use to write applications with .NET, and the syntax of C# was
inspired by C++, so C#, Java, and JavaScript, all three of these languages look somewhat similar.
Here is a snippet of C# code. This snippet contains many different concepts that we will investigate further
throughout this course, but let me give you a quick preview. This snippet of code is defining a method named Main.
A method is a place where you can organize your code so that you can call this method from other places and
force the code inside to execute and run. The code inside of this method is using the DateTime class,
which is part of the .NET Framework Class Library. I can use DateTime.Now to find out the current time,
and I can use .DayOFWeek after that to find out the current day of the week.
And if the current day of the week is equal to Monday, and we'll check that by using a double equal sign,
that checks to see if two values are equal, if the current day of the week is Monday, then we will branch
inside of this if statement and execute the code inside of the curly braces.
Inside of here we're calling another method, WriteLine. This method is attached to a console class,
also part of the FCL, so we're forcing WriteLine to execute, and we're passing it some data, a parameter.
We're passing it information that is going to write onto the screen.
In this case, it's going to write out the text, Another case of the Mondays!
But again, that only happens if the current day is a Monday. If the current day is not a Monday,
we don't execute the code inside of here. We come straight down to the bottom where the method will exit and
return without writing any information to the screen. Let's take code very similar to this code and place it
into a program that we can execute from the command line.