We've just used the command line C# compiler, csc.exe, and we gave the compiler one job that was to compile a
single file, hello.cs, but you can tell the compiler about multiple files to compile all at once.
And certainly when you start building real applications you don't want all of your code inside of a single file.
You'll take all of your code and spread it across multiple files, even across multiple directories,
and pass everything to csc.exe, which will produce a single executable or library.
When it comes to using multiple files, this is where Visual Studio is useful because Visual Studio can
manage all of those files and call the compiler for us, and we never have to worry about the details,
but it is good to know what happens behind the scenes. And it's also good to know with the C# Compiler is actually doing.
It's taking your C# code, and its transforming it into something called Microsoft Intermediate Language.
Some people will refer to this as M-S-I-L, or MSIL for short. MSIL defines instructions for the CLR.
It's the CLR's job then to read those instructions and transform those instructions into instructions that
the CPU on your machine will understand. So the processor that is inside your computer by itself, it cannot
execute the code that you write with .NET even after the compiler has transformed that code into an executable.
You need to have the CLR, the Common Language Runtime, to take those intermediate instructions inside an
executable and transform them into native instructions, native meaning the instructions work on the real
hardware where the program is running. All of that happens without us needing to do anything special,
and it's somewhat similar to what happens in the Java space, with Java compilers producing bytecode as an intermediate language.
But now that we know some of these low level details that are good to know, let's jump up into the space
we'll be working in for the rest of the course, which is inside of Visual Studio.