Now let's go into Windows and open up the Start menu and search for Visual because I want to launch
Visual Studio 2015 and create this hello world program in the Visual Studio environment.
And pretty much every application that you ever build with Visual Studio will start by saying File, New,
and then selecting this Project menu item. This will launch a dialogue that presents me with many different
project types that I can build across various languages that are supported by Visual Studio.
But I want to build a Visual C# application, specifically a Windows application, and even more specifically
a Console Application, so an application that runs form the command line.
Down here at the bottom of the dialogue I can select a Name for my project, I'm going to call it Hello,
and I will leave it inside of this default location, which is a project subfolder underneath of
documents/visual studio 2015, but you can place this anywhere on the hard drive that you like.
I will just select OK, and Visual Studio will go out and create this project for me.
Now depending on your configuration, you might have different windows that open up inside of Visual Studio.
I just really want to focus on one for right now, which is the Solution Explorer window.
I'm going to close everything else. And if for some reason you don't have the Solution Explorer window or
you accidently close the Solution Explorer window, you can always reopen this by going to the View menu.
Selecting this item will open that Solution Explorer window if it's not already open.
The Solution Explorer window is a window that organizes all of my code and all of my projects.
So the currently highlighted node in this tree in the Solution Explorer, this is my project.
It's called Hello. Inside of that project I have one source code file, one C# source code file called Program.cs.
I can click on any .cs file inside of Solution Explorer, double-click on it, and it will open over here in a
text editor window. And in bigger applications you'll have multiple .cs files inside of a project.
In fact, you'll probably have folders inside of your project and organize your source code files into folders.
And then project goes into a Solution, also named Hello, and in a larger application you can have multiple
projects inside of a Solution. We'll see both of those scenarios as the course progresses.
We'll work with multiple source code files; we will work with multiple projects inside of a Solution.
For right now, I just want to focus on Program.cs and recreating our Hello World application.
So the code that is inside of Program.cs looks a little bit different then what we wrote inside of Hello.cs.
For starters, there are quite a few namespaces that are listed here.
These are just namespaces that Visual Studio included by default because these are common namespaces that you
typically use on a day-to-day basis. There is no harm in leaving these namespaces here, but for right now
I'm just going to delete all of those namespaces. And then I'll point out that I also have a custom namespace here.
The namespace is Hello. Everything inside of the curly braces that delimit this namespace will be a part of
that namespace, so my class Program, it's full name now is not just Program, it's really Hello.Program.
And this program still has a method named Main, just like we had in Hello.cs.
We'll talk about this additional args thing here in just a minute.
For right now, I just want to use Console to do a WriteLine. And now we'll start to see one advantage of
using Visual Studio over Notepad. Visual Studio is constantly evaluating the code that you're writing with
every keystroke, and it's trying to detect anyway that it can help you write that code or if there's any
problems with that code. Right now it has detected a problem. It'll express that with a red squiggly line
that appears underneath of Console. And the problem here is that Visual Studio knows if you try to compile
this file that the compiler will not know what this Console thing is, and that's because, as we discussed
earlier, this Console class that we want to use, it's really system.console.
And if I come over here and click on this lightbulb, then whenever you see that lightbulb appear you can
click on it. That's Visual Studio's way of saying I might be able to help you with this problem, and it will
give you a big list of suggestions on how to fix this problem that Console does not exist.
The first suggestion is to add a using System to the top of the file.
That's the suggestion that I want to take because once I choose that the red squiggly goes away, at least the
red squiggly that's under Console, and now Visual Studio's just telling me that I need to do something with Console.
So let me backspace a bit and then hit period, and here's another way that Visual Studio tries to help you.
This is the IntelliSense window. Visual Studio knows about everything that you can do with a Console.
It knows that you can do things like set the cursor position, and it knows that I can do things like
WriteLine, so I'm going to select this method just by pressing enter because I want to write the string Hello, World.
So a string in C# is just a sequence of characters that appear between double quotes.
Almost every programming language has the concept of strings. Some languages use single quotes,
some languages use double quotes, C# is one of those languages where a string has to be inside of double quotes.
C# is also a case sensitive language, so Console, the C has to be uppercase; otherwise, you can see I get the red squiggly.
And the method call WriteLine, that has be an upper case W and an uppercase L.
But since I don't currently have any red squigglies on the screen, I should be able to run this program.
The easiest way to run a console application is to go to the Debug menu and say Start Without Debugging.
Visual Studio will automatically compile all of my source code, it will produce an executable, and then it
will launch that executable inside of a new console window. Visual Studio is also smart enough to add a
feature where you have to press a key for this console window to go away.
If that feature wasn't there, the console would just flash on the screen and go away immediately because my
program exits immediately after displaying Hello, World. But now that I can see this running, I will press
any key, and now I can come back and edit some more source code.
I also want to run this directly from the command line myself, and I can do that.
I can see down here in the Output window, which will appear anytime you build or run an application,
I can see in this window exactly where Hello.exe lives. It's underneath of the location that I specified in
the File, New, Project dialogue, and then it falls under a folder called Bin, which is short for binaries,
which are executable files that are on file system, bin\Debug\Hello.exe.
The Debug is here because by default Visual Studio will build your application in a way that makes it easy
to debug, that is easy to find problems and errors that occur during runtime.
We'll look at debugging in just a bit. For right now, I actually want to go to a console window and find
this directory, which is Visual Studio 2015\Projects\Hello\Hello\bin\Debug.
And if I do a directory of this folder, I can see inside of here, Hello.exe.
There are some additional files here, but again most of those are related to debugging.
I just want to be able to run Hello.exe from this folder and see that still works.
And I'm thinking it would be nice to be able to type Hello and run this program and also pass this program a
parameter like the name of a person so the program will say Hello Scott or Hello Alex.
Currently I don't have that ability. Every time I run the program it will just say Hello, World, but this is
easy enough to change. Whenever I type additional arguments to my program, those arguments will be passed
into my Main method in this method parameter names args. So just like WriteLine takes a parameter and I can
pass it something like Hello, World, this Main method can take a parameter.
In this case it is an array of strings, and the name of this parameter is args.
We will be talking in more detail about arrays later in this course, but for now just know that inside of a
console window I could do something like Hello Scott, Joy, Chris, Sarah, and I could keep typing words out
here, and when my program runs each of these will be an individual string inside of a collection of strings.
And this is the syntax in C# to say I don't have just one string, I can take 0 or more strings.
So if someone wants to pass me three names, those three names will be packaged up into this parameter called args.
Again, more on arrays later in this course, but these two square brackets indicate that I have an array of strings.
My ultimate goal is to pull out just the first string in that parameter and use that to write out a greeting here.
So let me show you something else I can do. Just before we do that, I'm going to add a double quote here
after Hello comma and a space, and then use the plus sign or an addition symbol to say Hello plus World.
The addition symbol does what you might think it would do. It's going to concatenate those two strings
together so that I get one string, Hello comma space World. And if I were to run this program Without
Debugging, I get the same output that I had before, Hello, World.
But now let's get this working with a name. So instead of concatenating this hard-coded string World,
I want to take the first argument out of this argument array and concatenate that after the string Hello comma.
Arrays in C# start with a base index of 0. That means to get the first element in an array you use the
square brackets, and you place a 0 inside. It's a common beginner mistake to ask for the first element of an
array by using args sub 1, but sub 1 would actually give you the second element in an array.
I want args sub 0. And after I do that I'm going to save the file, come back to the command line,
and type Hello Scott, and you'll notice I still get the text Hello, World.
That's because I was very careful to just save this program and not recompile the program, which means my
source code is different. But I never had Visual Studio build that source code into a new version of
Hello.exe, so I'm still running an older version of Hello.exe, I don't have a new one yet.
If I want to make sure that Visual Studio builds this, I can go to the Build menu and say Build Solution.
When you run the program from the Debug menu, Visual Studio automatically does the build, but if I'm going to
run from the command line like this, I have to explicitly ask Visual Studio to build, and now I should be
able to come out and say Hello Scott, and I can see Hello Scott, or Hello Joy, and I see Hello Joy.
And I now have a program that accepts some command line parameters from the user and uses those parameters to
change the display, to change its output.