Inside of ComputeStatistics in the GradeBook, I need to be able to work with this object
of type GradeStatistics.
I need to do some calculations and ultimately,
I will need to add some fields to that class
so that I can store the calculation somewhere.
So instead of returning an object immediately,
let me create a variable of type GradeStatistics.
We can call it stats, point it to that new instance
of GradeStatistics.
Then we'll need to write some code
to compute the statistics and then ultimately,
here at the bottom of the method,
we will return those statistics.
I know I need to find the highest grade, the lowest grade
and the average grade, so let's start by computing
the average grade.
We all know that to compute an average,
I need to sum all of the grades in the grades list
and then divided by the total number of grades.
So let me create a variable.
Let's call it sum and initialize it to zero.
This will represent the sum of all the grades
in the GradeBook, and now I need to go to each grade
that is in that GradeBook and add it to the sum.
There's an easy way to do this in C#,
and that is to use a foreach statement.
We will look at the statement in a little more depth
later in this course, but what I can do with a foreach
is say foreach grade in the grade collection,
please take that grade and put it into a variable for me.
And I can actually declare this variable inside
of the foreach statement.
Let's declare the variable, its name will be grade.
And I say foreach grade in this field grades,
then I apply some curly braces and here's what will happen.
Any code that I put inside of these curly braces
will execute once for each grade
that is in the grades collection.
If I have the grades 93, 85 and 80,
I'll execute the code inside of this foreach
once with the value 93 inside of grade,
and then with an 85 and then with an 80.
So we are looping over this code once for each grade.
And what I need to do with each grade is add that grade
to the sum, so I can say sum = sum
plus the current grade that I'm looking at.
And there's actually a shortcut syntax for this in C#.
I can say sum = sum + grade,
or I can say sum += grade,
and those two statements are equivalent.
So sum = sum + grade or sum += grade.
That will add the value of the grade into that sum variable,
and then I can compute the average just by taking the sum
and dividing it by the total number of grades
that are in the list, which I can get easily
because the list will tell me how many items it holds.
But where do I store that value?
That number, the AverageGrade,
is part of the statistics that I want to publish.
So it's probably something that I want to add
to the GradeStatistics class.
Let's come over there,
and I'm going to give this class three fields.
The AverageGrade, and I also need to store
the HighestGrade and the LowestGrade.
So these are three fields that will be present
for every instance of GradeStatistics.
And over in the GradeBook, I ultimately want to say
stats.AverageGrade equals the average,
except I don't have access to AverageGrade
because AverageGrade, remember,
if I don't specify an access modifier for a field or method,
the default is for that class member to be private.
So AverageGrade is only available
inside of the class, GradeStatistics.
I need to add public in front of all three of these fields.
Now earlier, I said you typically want
to encapsulate fields.
But in this case, the entire purpose of GradeStatistics
is to collect all those data together and expose it.
I'm going to make all three of these public.
There's an easy way to do that with Visual Studio.
I'm going to hold down the alt key on the keyboard
and then click the mouse to select
three rows inside of the editor.
And now when I type the word public,
I'm typing that across all three lines of code.
So just hold down the alt key and then click
and hold the mouse to select multiple lines of code.
So I now have three public fields inside of GradeStatistics,
and I should be able to say stats.AverageGrade.
I can see I have access to that now.
It will equal sum divided by,
and this is where I can walk up to that list of float,
the grades field, and one of the members that it has in here
is a member called Count, which will tell me exactly
how many items are in that list.
One thing I should be careful about is what happens
if there are no grades that have been entered?
What if I tried to divide by zero
because grades.Count is zero?
That would be a runtime error
and something that would crash the program.
This will be a line of code that I need to be careful about.
We're going to talk about error handling
in a later module of this course.
For now, we're just going to assume that the user
knows what they're doing
and they'll always add at least one grade to the gradebook
before they call ComputeStatistics.
If the user doesn't enter a grade, the program will crash
and say that it tried to divide something by zero.
But now we have the average grade computer.
What about the highest grade and the lowest grade?
In order to compute that, I'm going to need to keep track
of what is the highest grade that I've seen so far.
So as I'm looking at each grade inside of a foreach loop,
I need to compare that grade to some sort of record
that I've kept about the current highest grade.
And one way to do that would just be
to keep a running record of what is the highest grade
that I've seen so far.
I can do that directly on the stats class and say
let's initialize stats.HighestGrade to a very small value,
like zero, so that as we're executing the code
inside of here, we can always check to see
if the current grade is greater than stats.HighestGrade.
But many times, I want to examine a piece of code
and really think a minute about the responsibilities
about the line of code.
Where does this code belong?
Where should I initialize highest grade?
And I'm thinking that the initialization
of the highest grade and the lowest grade members
will ideally be inside of the GradeStatistics class itself.
I could do that by adding a constructor to this class.
So once again, the code snippet, ctor, press tab twice,
and I can now say inside of here
that HighestGrade = 0.
And notice I don't have to say stats
or access highest grade through some variable.
When you're inside of a class, you can always access
a member of that class without going through
some sort of variable.
More on that later, but HighestGrade now starts
as a very small value, and I need to initialize LowestGrade
ideally to some really high value.
Perhaps I could just initialize LowestGrade to 100.
I know all of my grades are between zero and 100,
but I do want to show you that on this float type,
there are some static members.
I can see that if I just type float.,
the IntelliSense window shows me some static members
that are available on the float type.
And one of the static members is max value.
That's the largest possible number that you could fit
into a variable of type float.
So I'm going to make LowestGrade this really high value,
and now I can come back to the GradeBook
and as I inspect each grade, I can see if that grade
is higher than the highest grade
or lower than the lowest grade.
I could do that with an if statement.
I could say if the grade is greater than
stats.HighestGrade, only then will I execute
the following code.
We've talked about if statements and branching execution
earlier in the course.
It's inside of here where I would say okay,
the new highest grade for stats
will be the grade that I'm currently looking at.
This is one way to write the code.
But let me show you another approach.
I'm going to remove the if statement,
and now I'm going to use another class
of the .NET framework, the Math class.
Math also has some static members,
members that make it easy to compute a cosine
or a sine, raise a number to a power and so forth.
It also has these static members, max and min.
These are methods that I can invoke.
And what I do when I invoke Math.Max
is I pass in two numbers, and Math.Max will return
the highest or the maximum of those two numbers.
So if I just pass in grade and stats.HighestGrade
and assign the result of this operation
to stats.HighestGrade, stats.HighestGrade will contain
the highest number of these two.
I can also do this to set the lowest grade.
So the lowest grade would equal Math.Min,
or the minimum value between grade and stats.LowestGrade.
And now we have some code that will loop over
all of the grades in our grade collection,
keep track of the highest grade its seen,
the lowest grade its seen;
and also compute a sum so that it can compute an average.
Once all those numbers are put together
inside of the GradeStatistics object,
we'll return it from ComputeStatistics,
and now I should be able to come over into my program
and use those statistics.
Let's remove some of those code we added earlier,
and I just want to write out the stats.
First I will also add another grade.
Let's add a grade of 75,
then we will compute statistics.
And I want to write out the average, the highest
and the lowest.
One way to do a Console.WriteLine really quickly
is to use another code snippet, a cw snippet.
All I need to do is type the characters cw, press tab twice,
and I now have a line of code to invoke Console.WriteLine.
Let's write out stats.AverageGrade
and then Console.WriteLine, stats.HighestGrade
and Console.WriteLine, stats.LowestGrade.
I want to run this program without the debugger
so Control + F5 will do that,
or go to the Debug menu.
And the results I get out would show me that
the average grade is an 85.16.
The highest grade is a 91, the lowest grade is a 75,
this whole looks correct.
I should change the output so that I put some
additional text in front of these numbers
to tell the user exactly what numbers they're seeing,
but it does look like the gradebook
is doing the right computations,
and that's all thanks to a couple of classes
that we've implemented: the GradeBook and GradeStatistics.
Also, thanks to some static members on types
in the .NET Framework,
things like Float.MaxValue and Math.Min.
And we now have a GradeBook with some minimal features
but it's something that we can build on
throughout the rest of this course.