In this module, we looked at quite a few features of the C# language.
We learned how to create a class definition
and give a class a constructor.
A constructor is a special method used when we create
an instance of the class using the new keyword.
We also learned how we can construct multiple instances
of the class, and we can have variables that point
to these instances, these objects.
Two variables can point to the same object,
but also point to two different objects.
We also learned about the public and private
access modifiers.
Those play an important role in encapsulation.
And most importantly, we talked about taking
some requirements for a GradeBook
and using those requirements to create classes
like GradeBook and GradeBook statistics.
Over time, you'll figure out that these syntax
of a programming language,
while it can be challenging to learn,
can always be mastered over time.
What's a little more difficult is learning
good programming practices.
That requires you to always think about
the responsibilities of each class and method
and which class is going to encapsulate and be responsible
for which feature.
We're going to continue to build on our GradeBook
and touch on those topics throughout the rest of the course.