When you sit down to write a class in C#,
it's usually because you need to write some code
to create a program for something that you need
or something your business needs.
So pretend someone comes to you
with the following requirements:
We need an electronic grade book to read the scores
of an individual student and then compute
some simple statistics from the scores.
The grades are entered as floating point numbers
from zero to 100, and the statistics should show us
the highest grade, the lowest grade and the average grade.
These requirements describe the program we need to write,
but where do we get started?
Well, fundamentally, C# is a language
where you write classes to implement features
in your software, so these requirements will force us
to write at least one class and to use other classes
that have already been written for us
by the framework class library.
But what class should we write?
This is one of the toughest questions to answer
if you are new to programming.
But generally, we use classes to create abstractions
for the different nouns that we need to work with,
or a noun is a person, a place, a thing, an idea.
So when I scan through the requirements,
a noun like grade book will instantly jump out at me
because it is a noun that the business is using.
It's in the requirements, and it would seem like
a good place to get started is to create a class
named grade book that will implement the functionality
to store grades and compute statistics.
Let's get started on these requirements
by creating a new project.
So once again, I'll go to the File, New Project menu.
Once again, I want a console application,
and I'm going to give the project the name Grade,
with the capital G.
I'll let Visual Studio create this project for me and
Visual Studio will give me my first class.
The program class, just like we saw in the last module,
here's the mean method on that program class.
That's the entry point for the application,
and that's where I want to use a grade book class
that I'm going to create.
So where do I put the GradeBook class?
Well, it's perfectly legal to define multiple classes
inside of the same file, but most C# developers
will follow a convention where each class
gets its own individual file.
So I'm going to right-click the project that opens up
this context menu, and then I can say
let's add a class to this project.
The dialog that opened contains a number of templates
for all sorts of different things that you can add
to a project, but I just want to add a class.
And down here, I can give that class a name,
give this file a name.
It's going to be GradeBook.cs.
And by convention, the file will have the same name
as the class.
So Visual Studio has already given me
a class definition here.
The class is GradeBook.
A class definition always starts with the class keyword
and then the name of the class.
Everything between these curly braces then will be
what we call members of this class,
just like this class is nested inside of a namespace
called Grades, so GradeBook is a member of grades.
And here at the top, we have a number of using statements.
We won't use classes from all of those namespaces,
but I'll leave them there because they don't hurt anything.
And now inside of GradeBook, anything that I add here
will be a member of the class.
And class members broadly fall into one of two categories.
One category would be members of this class
that hold state or data, because state is the data
that you need to work with inside of the class.
The state for GradeBook would be the grades
that a user is entering for a student.
So somewhere inside of this GradeBook,
I'm going to need to store each grade as it is entered,
and then the other category of class members
would be behavior-related members,
that is members that do work.
These members are typically methods,
methods that I want to write to allow someone
to interact with a GradeBook and ask it to do something
like add a grade or compute statistics.
The class is a noun, and methods that do work on that class
are typically verbs, like AddGrade, ComputeStatistics.
So they are members that start with a verb.
And let's start by adding a member that will allow me
to add a grade into the GradeBook.
I'll do that first by using two C# keywords,
public and void.
We will circle back later and talk about
what those two keywords mean,
and I'm going to create a method called AddGrade.
It's a method because it's going to have
parentheses at the end.
And then there's an opening curly brace
and a closing curly brace.
Everything that goes between those curly braces
will be the code that executes when someone
invokes this method and executes this method.
The parentheses here contain the parameter list
for this method, that is, what is the data
that someone wants to pass into this method?
Right now, this method doesn't take any parameters,
but obviously when I want to add a grade to the GradeBook,
I will need to take some data, which is the grade,
and I could do that by asking someone to pass in
an integer value.
Let's call it grade.
And you can see that defining this parameter
is very much like how we defined a variable
in the last module.
I have to give that parameter a type, which is integer,
and I have to give that parameter a name, which is grade.
But in this case, the requirements did say
that these grades would be floating point numbers,
and integer is not a good way to hold
a floating point number.
There's a couple other classes that .NET provides
that I should use for floating point numbers.
There is double, which is a double precision
floating point number; and there's float,
which takes up less space, it's a single precision
floating point number.
And for this application, float should be good enough.
We'll have a high enough precision.
And at this point, this grade variable will be available
throughout the rest of the method.
We say that it is scoped to this method
between these two curly braces.
I cannot use it anywhere outside of those curly braces,
but I can use this parameter, grade,
which I can just think of now as a variable
anywhere inside the curly braces.
I could, for instance, say
grade = grade + 5.
That would add five points to every grade
before we store it, but I don't need to do that.
What I really need to do is store this grade,
make it part of the state of this class.
I don't know how many grades
someone will pass to me ultimately.
They can invoke AddGrade 10 times.
I would need to store all 10 grades.
And I'll need access to those grades outside of this method,
outside of AddGrade, because when someone calls
a different method, ComputeStatistics,
the parameter grade won't be available.
So I need to store that somewhere.
And to do that, I'll use another class
from the framework class library,
one that is in the namespace System.Collections.Generic.
As the name of that namespace implies,
this namespace is full of collection classes,
that is, classes that allow you to store multiple things.
One such collection is the list collection.
A list can store zero items or 10 items or 1000 items.
But before I can use a list, I have to tell the list
what type of items it's going to be storing.
Is it going to be storing a list of strings
or a list of integers?
Or a list of floating point numbers?
That's what I want because the grades are being
passed to me as floating point numbers.
Later in this course, I'll describe exactly
what this syntax means, this syntax with the angle brackets.
It's part of what we call the generic type syntax in C#,
but that's a preview for a later module
when I talk about generics.
For right now, you can think about this as a list
that can hold zero or more floating point numbers.
And this is going to be one of the members of the class
that holds the state for the class.
It's what we would call a field.
So right now, we have a method called AddGrade,
and this is going to be a field.
And just like a method, this field has to have a name.
I'm going to call it grades for now.
For fields, the naming convention is to use lowercase names.
And to place a grade into this collection of grades,
I just need to come into my method and say grades,
and that will be available to me inside of this method
because grades is a member of the class.
And once I hit the period character,
the IntelliSense window pops up to show me
all of the different things that I can do with a list.
That includes things like clear the list, to empty it out,
flush all the grades out.
I could also sort the list in some specific order.
But what I want to do is just to add something to the list.
I want to add the grade that is being passed in
to the AddGrade method.
Now there's at least one more thing that we have to do
to make this class usable, but we'll see that next.
For right now, I just want you to know that this is how
you create classes.
I now have two classes in this project,
Program and GradeBook.
The project system in Visual Studio will make sure
both of these files go to the C# compiler,
which will compile them both into my application.
And each of these classes, GradeBook and Program,
they both have their own file to live in
with a .cs extension.
And in this GradeBook class, we have one method
and we have one field.
Throughout this course, we'll discover other types
of members that we can add to a class.
But for right now, let's work with this method in this field.