Let's return to Program.cs and the main method which is the entry point
for the application.
And now that I have a class, GradeBook,
I can have define variables of type GradeBook.
And the name of this variable could be GradeBook or Grades.
Let's just call it book.
And through that variable,
I should be able to invoke methods
like the AddGrade method that we gave a GradeBook,
and I can pass in a parameter to that method.
Let's pass in a 91.
Now if I were to build the application at this point,
I would get a compiler error,
and Visual Studio is already indicating
that there's going to be an error
with the red squiggly line.
And the error is the use of an unassigned
local variable, book.
Once I have a class definition,
I can use that to create variables like book.
But just by adding a variable of type book to this method,
that doesn't give me an actual GradeBook.
All it does is give me a variable that I can use
to access a GradeBook.
And here's an important concept in C#
that we will talk about several times in this course.
When I create a class definition,
I can think of that class definition like a cookie-cutter.
A cookie-cutter allows me to create one or more cookies
with a specific shape just by applying the cutter
to some dough.
And its cookies that I really want to work with and eat,
but cookie-cutter only exists to create cookies
with a consistent and specific shape.
A class definition is similar to this
because I don't do any actual work
with the class definition, but I can use the class
to create objects with a specific and consistent shape
and then work with those objects.
The class is a cookie-cutter.
But instead of stamping out cookies from dough,
a class will stamp out objects
from the memory of the computer.
And it objects that I need to work with in my program.
It is objects that are allocated into the memory
of my computer and hold the data that I need.
The way I create a real GradeBook object
using that GradeBook class is to use another keyword in C#,
the new keyword.
And I'll say new GradeBook.
Literally, I am asking for a new instance
of this GradeBook class, and I'm going to store a reference
to that object, this new GradeBook object,
in the variable book.
I'm also going to apply a parenthesis here,
and it looks like I'm invoking a method.
That's because behind the scenes,
I actually am invoking a method.
I'm using the name of the class, GradeBook,
and then applying parentheses.
Behind the scenes, that will invoke what's known
as a constructor.
And a constructor is responsible for creating a new instance
of this GradeBook by allocating memory
and initializing the state inside.
We are going to talk more about instructors in just a bit.
But now that I've created a new GradeBook
and I've assigned that to book,
that takes care of the uninitialized variable,
that is, a variable that just wasn't assigned anything.
The C# compiler was smart enough to know
that, that variable was going to create a problem,
it didn't point to an actual GradeBook.
And now let me try to run this program with the debugger
to see if we can add a grade.
I'll do that just by pressing F5 to run with the debugger.
And after Visual Studio builds the project,
it will start the application running and
we will get an exception inside of our AddGrade method.
This exception is a NullReferenceException.
Is an exception that you are sure to see many times
over the course of a career in C# programming.
And in this case, it means I'm using
an uninitialized variable, and that uninitialized variable
is the field, grades, that I have inside of GradeBook.
Let me stop the debugger
and show you that Visual Studio tried to indicate
that this was going to be a problem.
It did that with a warning or a green squiggly line.
It's not an error because the C# compiler
cannot tell with 100% accuracy that this was going
to create a problem.
It was able to do that inside of Program.cs
with this very simple logic before I had new GradeBook.
The C# compiler knew that book was uninitialized
and I was certainly going to have a problem.
In the case of the class, it wasn't so clear.
But I did get a warning here that this grades field
was never assigned to and will always have
the default value, null, which means I will not have
an object that is a list of floating point numbers.
I will have a variable that points to nothing.
There's nothing I can do with it.
Just like with the GradeBook in Program.cs,
I have to make sure that this field is initialized
and actually points to an object,
a list of float that will do real work.
And once again, I can do that with a new keyword.
So I could say this list of floats
should be initialized and start off
with a new object that is constructed for me,
because now the C# compiler can see that this field
is assigned to.
And now I'm pretty sure that this program should work,
and I'm so sure that I want to come back to Program.cs
and actually add another grade here.
Let me add the grade,
89.5.
And I just want to show you another interesting
error message.
If I hover over this error, I can see that
the argument I'm passing to AddGrade is getting an error,
cannot convert from double to float.
So when we defined AddGrade,
we said that when someone invokes this method,
they need to pass us a number that is typed as float,
which is a single precision floating point number.
But when I use this literal value here, 89.5,
by default, that's going to be a double precision
floating point number, a double.
And the C# compiler, it's very picky about types.
Now 91, this integer value,
the C# compiler will allow me to pass that value
into AddGrade, because it will implicitly convert that value
into a float.
Any integer value will convert to a float,
but the C# compiler is not going to do that
with the double precision floating point number.
It's not going to try to place it or convert it
into a single precision floating point number
because you might lose some information.
This is just like if I declared a variable of type double
and I initialized it with a value 91.5,
that's going to work just fine.
But if I change this type to float,
that will be an error.
What I need to do is I need to tell the C# compiler
that this value should be treated
as a floating point number.
And the way I can do that is by appending an F
at the end of this number.
And now that line of code would work,
so let me also apply an F here to AddGrade.
And now let's set a breakpoint here
at the bottom of the program.
I'll press F5 to run with the debugger,
and I just want to inspect my variable book
to see what's inside.
I can see that, that grades field
has two items inside of it
and that the grades are 91 and 89.5.
So now I know that the GradeBook
is successfully storing my grades.
And that's good, we have a working GradeBook.
Now let's go back and talk about the construction
of this GradeBook just a bit.