When I use the new keyword and then the name of the class
with parentheses, this is instantiating an instance
of that class, it's creating an object.
And instantiating a class will invoke a special method
we call a constructor, because a constructor
helps construct an object.
Every class will have a default constructor
that exists implicitly, unless I do something special.
And this is why I can create an instance of GradeBook
and use it even though I don't have a constructor
explicitly defined in that class.
If I do want to define my own constructor,
it's very much like defining a method.
I'll use the public keyword and then the name of the class
followed by parentheses.
Just like a method, I had those parentheses
at the end of my curly braces to denote the start
and the end of the method.
There are many scenarios where you will want to write
your own constructor for a class,
because writing your own constructor gives you control
over the initialization of an object.
You can initialize fields and data for the object.
You can set default values.
You can create other objects that your object uses.
And you can even have multiple constructors defined,
but we'll look at that later in the course.
For now, let's look at implementing a constructor
for our GradeBook.
Currently in my program, when I say new GradeBook,
we will be using an implicit constructor
that is defined for us, because we never wrote
an explicit constructor for GradeBook.
But now let's take control over the initialization
of a GradeBook, and write a constructor.
There's a very easy way to do this in Visual Studio.
If I just typed ctor,
those characters are recognized as one of the code snippets
in Visual Studio.
What a code snippet allows you to do is just type
some short sequence of characters, like ctor,
and this is the code snippet for a constructor.
And if I press tab twice,
Visual Studio will do a little bit of code generation
and write the constructor for me.
I already have the public keyword in place,
and a constructor is a method definition
where the method name is the same as the class.
Like every method, it has some parentheses
where I can take parameters, and then the opening
and closing curly braces.
There's some other snippets that we'll see
throughout this course, but ctor,
that's one I use every day.
It's short for constructor, that's easy to remember.
And now it's inside of this constructor
where I can take explicit control over the initialization
of my object.
It turns out we're already doing some initialization
during the construction of a GradeBook,
because when we defined this field,
this field being grades, I'm using what's known
as a field initializer syntax here.
I'm saying I want a field named grades,
and I want to immediately initialize it to a new list
for each GradeBook that is constructed.
So each GradeBook maintains its own list of grades.
Instead of using field initializer syntax,
I could cut this line of code out of here
and inside of the constructor, say
grade equals a new list of float.
For the most part, it doesn't matter if you use
that field initializer syntax or if you initialize
a field and constructor.
There's no obvious differences in terms of performance.
It really comes down to the syntax
that you're most comfortable with,
and also some special circumstances.
For example, in a constructor, since it is a method,
I can take some parameters here like maybe I want
the maximum grade or the maximum number of items
that I'm going to store in a grade,
and then I need that parameter to pass along
to other constructors.
That's a case where I probably wouldn't use
field initializer syntax.
I would use explicit initialization inside of a constructor.
But for right now, let's keep what is known
as a default constructor.
A default constructor is a constructor
that doesn't take any parameters.
So when someone initializes a GradeBook
and creates an instance using the new keyword,
they don't have to pass any parameters that arrive here
to the constructor method.
Just like I'm using the default constructor
for a list of float, I'm using the new keyword
and invoking that constructor,
and I don't pass any parameters along.
And the important concept to take away here
is that GradeBook is a class, it's a blueprint
for creating objects.
It's a cookie-cutter.
In order to get an object that is an instance
of this GradeBook class, something that I can use
and something that I can actually add grades to,
I need to create an object.
And I do that using the new keyword.
I want a new GradeBook or a new list of float.
And now that we know a little bit more about constructors,
let's really drill into the details about the differences
between objects and variables.