One topic I want to make clear before removal
is the distinction between a class and a variable.
A class is a blueprint for creating objects.
I can use the new keyword with the GradeBook class,
and that creates a GradeBook object for me in memory.
And that GradeBook and hold a list of grades.
I can also use a class to define the type of a variable,
because in C#, every variable needs a type,
and a class defines a particular type.
We'll see other categories of types in this course.
A class is just one way to create a type.
But when I use a class to type a variable,
it's because I want to remember some specific object
when I'm inside of a method.
I want to remember the GradeBook so that I can add grades
to that specific object and eventually ask it
to compute some statistical results.
You can think of the variable as a storage location
that points to a specific object.
Let's make that concept a little more concrete
using the debugger.
Inside the application, I've created a new GradeBook
and I'm holding on to that book
through a variable named book.
But what would happen after I add these two grades
to that GradeBook if I reassign that variable
and said book is now equal to new GradeBook?
And to make things interesting, let's add a grade
to that GradeBook, something different than we have.
So just a 75.
And now I'll press F10 to start the debugger.
F10 will step through each line of code.
I want to step until I get to the bottom of the program,
and I want to investigate this book variable.
Now the question is, does this book variable
point to a GradeBook that holds two grades,
the 91 and the 89.5?
Or does it hold one grade, the 75?
Or does it hold three grades?
And the answer is, if I hover over book,
I can see there's one grade inside, it is the 75.
And that's because this line of code I added,
book = new GradeBook,
that's creating a brand-new instance of a GradeBook,
a second instance.
And this new GradeBook will start with an empty
list of grades until I add that first grade, the 75.
And that is now the object that this book variable refers to
throughout the rest of the method.
And the lesson is that when I declare a variable
of type GradeBook, that variable isn't stuck
referring to a single object throughout its lifetime.
That's why it is a variable.
I can take the variable and point it
to any GradeBook object that I have available,
and then I can invoke methods and do other
interesting things with that variable.
And in this program now, I've created two
separate GradeBook instances.
But by the time I reach this line of code,
I only have access to the second instance.
I don't have any variables that refer to that first
GradeBook that I created.
There's no way to get back to that, and it's become garbage.
That's what we call objects that are no longer being used
by the program, and the Common Language Runtime
is smart enough to periodically scan through memory
and figure out which objects are garbage.
The CLR can then clean those objects up and free up memory
so that we have more space for other objects.
This is just like cleaning up a hard drive
by removing files that you no longer need.
You remove files and make space for new files
that you're going to use.
But what happens if I want access
to two different GradeBooks?
Well, that's when I would need two different variables.
So let's call this variable book2.
And since this is a new variable, I'm going to need
to properly declare that variable and provide a type.
So book2 is a variable of type GradeBook.
And now let me right click on the bottom of this program
and say run to cursor.
That's another easy way to get the debugger
just to run to a specific point in your code.
And now I can investigate book2
and see that it has my one grade, the 75.
But I still have access to the first GradeBook
through the book variable, and that's still holding on
to the two grades that I put inside of there.
And now let's try one more experiment.
Instead of staying book2 equals a new GradeBook,
let's say book2 = book.
And the right question to ask would be to figure out
if this is making a copy of the original GradeBook.
In other words, will I now have two objects
of type GradeBook, one with two grades in it?
And will book2, will that GradeBook have three grades in it
or one grade in it?
I'll show you the answer in the next clip.