When we define a class in C#,
we are creating something that is called a reference type.
We will explore another category of types
later in the course, but reference types
are important to understand in C#
because when we have a variable that is typed
as a class like GradeBook, which is a reference type,
the variable gives us a place to remember the GradeBook.
But the variable does not hold the GradeBook itself.
The GradeBook is somewhere else in memory,
and the variable holds a pointer to that object in memory.
The variable literally contains a memory address.
So imagine the table on the right-hand side of the screen
representing a section of memory on your computer,
and each memory location has an address like
six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
There are billions of these memory cells.
Let's say when we create the GradeBook object,
the runtime placed the start of the object
at location eight in our computer.
That means the book1 variable, you can think of it
as holding the value eight, which indicates where
the GradeBook lives inside of those billions
of memory addresses in the computer.
It's like when someone gives you their business card,
you don't hold the other person, you hold a pointer
or an address and something that can lead you
to that person when you need to talk to them
or you need them to do something for you.
A variable for a reference type holds a pointer.
And when I do something like invoke a method
with .AddGrade, the runtime takes care
of following that pointer for me
and invoking the correct method on the proper object.
One important implication of reference types
is that I can have multiple variables
all pointing to the same object.
If I use a line of code like book2 = book1,
then the runtime will copy the value of the book1 variable
into book2, which means the runtime will copy
the memory address, eight, into book2.
And now I can use both book1 and book2
to interact with the exact same GradeBook object.
Let's take a look at this scenario with the debugger.
At the end of the last clip, I included this line of code
in the project that says book2 = book.
And the way to think about this is that the value
that is inside of book is copied and placed into book2.
But you must always remember with C#,
that the value inside of book is not a GradeBook object.
It's just a pointer to a GradeBook object.
So what I'm doing is I'm copying that pointer
into another variable, and both book and book2
should now be referencing the same GradeBook.
I can verify that by right clicking and saying
run to cursor here at the bottom of the main method.
And if we look inside of book, we will see it has
three grades, 91, 89.5, and then the 75 was added through
the book2 variable, because book2 points
to the exact same GradeBook.
Now one thing that might have occurred to you
as we've been using the debugger is:  why can the debugger
see the grades that are inside of a GradeBook,
but I cannot see those same grades if I stop debugging
and try to access those grades through
one of these variables?
For instance, if I say book2.grades,
this isn't available in the IntelliSense list.
The only thing I can get to is really AddGrade
on that book2 variable; and the same goes
for the book variable.
So what is it that makes AddGrade available to me
but not the grades field that is the list of float
that is inside of a GradeBook?
Let's talk about that topic next.