I'd like you to be familiar with all of the keywords
in the program that we've been writing
before we leave this module, and we've already talked about
keywords like namespace and class.
But one keyword we haven't talked about
is the public keyword that appears in a few places.
C# was designed as an object-oriented language,
meaning it has a built-in syntax to make it easy to define
and work with objects, like this GradeBook.
The class we wrote defines a blueprint for creating objects
of type GradeBook.
And one fundamental pillar of object-oriented programming
is encapsulation.
We use objects that encapsulate the behavior
in the data that we need the software to perform.
Encapsulation means we are enclosing or hiding
certain details of how the software works.
Since some details will be hidden from me
when I use an object, I don't need to worry about
those details, and I can be a little more productive.
Software has a tendency to become very complex,
and some applications are so complex,
it's impossible for one person to know all of the details
inside of every class.
So encapsulation plays an extremely important role
in software because I can work with objects
that other people have written without knowing the details
of how those objects are implemented.
Even a simple class like GradeBook,
which has an AddGrade method,
that encapsulates how the GradeBook is actually
storing a grade.
When I use a GradeBook object, I don't care if the grade
is stored in memory or on disk or in a database
in the cloud, the GradeBook actually stores
the grades in a list.
And as I pointed out in the last clip,
I can access this AddGrade method from code
inside of my program, but I cannot access the list of grades
in code that is outside of this GradeBook class.
That's because of the keyword public that appears in front
of the AddGrade method.
Public is what we call an access modifier.
Access modifiers are keywords in C#,
and public is one modifier.
Another access modifier is private.
As the names imply, public makes a class member
publicly available so that someone can reach and invoke
a public member like AddGrade from outside of this class.
But if I don't explicitly specify the access modifier
for a member of the class, the default is to make
the member private.
And that means the member is only usable from code
inside of the same class.
This is why inside of AddGrade, I can use the grades list,
but no one outside of GradeBook can see this field.
We can say that the storage for grades is encapsulated
inside of the GradeBook.
We'll see how this works in code in just a bit.
And I want you to know that public and private
are just two of the available access modifiers.
We'll cover more modifiers later in the course.
For now, let's take a closer look at public and private.
These are arguably the two most important access modifiers.
Inside of our application, let's see what would happen
if I were to add the public keyword to my grades field.
Now I will tell you, if you make a member public,
you typically want to expose that member
with an uppercase letter.
I'm not going to do that for now because we're not
going to leave the public modifier here,
but an uppercase letter would be the convention.
Now back in Program.cs, I would have the ability
to look at the grades through either the book variable
or the book2 variable.
And this is usually not what you want to do.
You typically want to encapsulate your field
and encapsulate your data inside of an object.
So I'm going to come back to the GradeBook and remove
that public access modifier.
And now if we take a look at Program.cs,
I can see the red squiggly line because
GradeBook.grades is inaccessible
due to its protection level.
These access modifiers you can think about using them
to apply protection and encapsulate certain aspects
of your objects.
If you're defining a member of a class, like AddGrade,
and you do not provide an access modifier,
that class member will be a private member.
So now, I cannot even access AddGrade
outside of the GradeBook.
So AddGrade is certainly something that I want to be public.
I also want the constructor to be public.
Otherwise, the code inside of Program.cs
wouldn't be able to instantiate a GradeBook.
The constructor would be hidden,
and many people like to be very explicit
when they define a field and use the private keyword
so that when you're looking through the code,
it's very obvious that grades is going to be
a private member of this class.
If I did want to hide AddGrade, I could use
the private keyword here also.
But this is how I want to design the class.
I want the constructor and the AddGrade method
to be public numbers.
I want the grades, the list of float that stores my data,
I want that to be private;
and that gives me some encapsulation.
So we're just about ready to add some more features
to our GradeBook, but before we do let's take a look
at one more keyword.