One more keyword I want to make you aware of in C#
is the static keyword.
The static keyword is a bit of an advanced topic,
which we'll return to in a later module to see
in more detail.
But I want to give you a basic introduction now
to explain some of the code that we've seen already
and some of the code that we still need to write.
Members of a class can be marked as static,
meaning static is a keyword that you can apply
to a method or field.
The code on the screen, imagine it inside
of the GradeBook class.
It is defining two publicly available fields,
one called minimum grade and one called maximum grade.
And it's using that field initializer syntax
to initialize these fields to zero and 100, respectively.
These fields are static fields,
and here's what's important about a static field.
A static field or method is something you can access in code
without creating an instance of a class.
Generally speaking, to do any useful work with a class,
you need to use the new keyword to call a constructor
and create an instance of the class,
but there are classes out there with static members
that can do work without creating an instance.
Instead, you reference the field or the method
using the type name, and then the name of the field
or the method.
So GradeBook.MaximumGrade is an expression
that returned 100.
And I don't need an instance of GradeBook to use that.
This is how Console.WriteLine works.
Console is a class, but I don't need to create
an instance of console to use the class.
It has static methods that I can reach
and invoke, like WriteLines.
I just use the name of the class and then a dot.
So Console.WriteLine.
I will warn you now that you have to be a little bit careful
about using statics.
They can have some unfortunate and negative impacts
on the design of your software.
We'll talk about some of the ramifications of static
later in the course, but right now I wanted to make you
aware of what was happening with that static keyword
and how we were invoking code like Console.WriteLine.
And we'll use this knowledge in the next clip
when we add some more features to the GradeBook.