What I'd like to do next is figure out how to get
statistics out of the GradeBook.
Remember the requirements wanting to know
for a given set of grades,
what's the highest score, the lowest score
and the average score?
Sometimes, when I'm not sure what to do,
I make stuff up and then I see if I can get it to work.
For example, I'm thinking if I want a GradeBook
to compute statistics, then that phrase,
ComputeStatistics, it's a pretty good
verb-oriented behavior that I can add to a GradeBook
as a method.
It's very clear when I look at a piece of code like this
what the GradeBook will be doing.
But what will the GradeBook do with those statistics?
Will it store those statistics internally?
Will it expose them somehow so I could see something
like the lowest grade that is associated with the GradeBook?
But if I can walk up to a GradeBook at any time
and look at the lowest grade, then why doesn't the GradeBook
just compute statistics for me all of the time
after each grade is added?
This is where you just have to think about
how are people going to use your objects?
How do people want to use your classes?
And here's how I think I would want to solve this problem.
I do want to call a method called ComputeStatistics.
I do want that word to be explicit
because the program has reached a point where
all of the grades are entered and now,
I want to generate those statistics so I can display them
to the user.
But I don't want those statistics to be part
of the GradeBook, and I don't want something called
lowest score to be part of the GradeBook.
I'd rather have ComputeStatistics return statistics to me
or have that method return some object to me
that will hold the statistics that I need.
That way, the GradeBook is just responsible
for storing the grades and computing the statistics.
And I have another object that is responsible for
and encapsulates the statistical results themselves.
Sometimes, we talk about encapsulation as hiding things
and certainly, this method, ComputeStatistics
will hide the algorithms that I need to compute
the statistics, and that's nice.
But encapsulation can also be the concept of
surrounding something, putting information together
into a single context and into one place,
and that's what I want the statistics to be.
In other words, perhaps what I really want here
is to write a new class, GradeStatistics
so that I can define a variable.
Let's call it stats.
And when I call ComputeStatistics, I can store a reference
to the computed results inside of the stats variable.
This gives me a separation between the active
computing statistics and the result of those calculations.
It does mean I'm going to have to create another class,
GradeStatistics, but many times you can reduce
the complexity of an application by adding more classes.
The GradeBook will now hold the grades.
This GradeStatistics class will hold
statistical information.
So Let's see if we can get this to run or at least compile.
So I'll come into the grades project and add another class.
So select class and this add new item dialog.
This will be called GradeStatistics.CS.
I don't actually have to put the .cs into this dialog box.
Visual Studio will do that for me.
Now I have this class.
If I come back to Program.cs,
you can see I don't have an error anymore.
Visual Studio now knows what GradeStatistics is,
but we still don't have a ComputeStatistics
on our GradeBook.
So let's add that.
I will expect this to be a public method
so I can invoke it from outside of GradeBook.
And I expect this method to return an object
of type GradeStatistics.
That's another key that we haven't talked about yet,
but public is an access modifier and then
just before the method name, you always have to describe
what a method returns.
In this case, I'm going to have a method
named ComputeStatistics,
and this method will return an object
of type GradeStatistics.
If a method doesn't need to return anything,
you can use the void keyword to say that this method
doesn't return a value.
So now we've learned another keyword in the C# language.
And when you write a constructor,
that's the only method that you ever write
where you do not specify a return type.
It's just an access modifier
and then the name of the constructor,
which is always the same as the name of the class.
That makes constructors look a little bit different.
So AddGrade doesn't return anything.
Compute statistics will return a GradeStatistics object.
And right now, Visual Studio will give me an error
because ComputeStatistics does not return a value.
It's an error to say you'll return GradeStatistics
but then not have a return statement inside of the method.
For right now, let's just return
a new instance of GradeStatistics.
We'll need to populate this and do some computations.
But for right now, I'm just trying to get the program
to build, and I should be able to, at this point,
build the solution.
We are not actually computing any statistics,
but that's okay.
Sometimes in software, you just have to feel your way
through to the final solution,
and I think, looking at this code,
that we're on the right track to computing some statistics.
In the next clip, we can take a closer look at this method
and figure out how we actually are
going to do these computations.