Earlier in this course I showed you how to use the C# compiler from the command line.
Remember, the compiler's name is csc.exe, and I can pass one or more C# source code files to csc,
and the compiler will produce an executable that I can run in a command window.
That's how we wrote a hello world program in the first module. Now technically what the C# compiler produces
is called an assembly. A .NET assembly is a file that contains our compiled code, code that can execute
under the supervision of the Common Language Runtime. When we are writing a simple program like the Grade
Book program that we've been working on, we don't need to think about assemblies.
We can just compile and run our program. But on more sophisticated projects, we do need to learn a bit more
about how to make and also use other assemblies. .NET assemblies are just files that you will store on disk with a
.exe or .dll extension. Exe is short of executable. An exe file is a file that you can execute directly
by double-clicking on the file in Windows or using the name of the program from the command line.
The .dll extension is short for dynamic-link library. A dll is a file that you cannot execute directly,
but another program can load a dll and use the code inside, which means one reason to put code inside of a
dll is when you are writing code that you want to reuse in multiple applications.
A good example of a reuse is the .NET Framework itself. Some of the classes we've been using,
classes like Console and DateTime, they live inside an assembly that .NET provides.
The assembly's name is MSCorLib.dll. It is a core library that contains core types.
And many of this cor .NET assemblies like MSCorLib, they live inside a place known as the Global Assembly
Cache on a Windows machine. You will find the Global Assembly Cache underneath your Windows folder where
Windows installs inside a folder named Assembly. Inside of there you'll see additional folders beginning
with the letters G-A-C, GAC for short. That's what we call the Global Assembly Cache, the GAC.
The assemblies stored in the GAC are available to use from any .NET program that runs on a machine.
That's why popular assemblies like MSCorLib, which has the Console and DateTime classes, as well as classes
like String, these assemblies live in the GAC, so there's only one copy for the entire machine.
And now that we know that our GradeBook program is a .NET assembly and that we use classes from other
assemblies like MSCorLib, let's take a look in Visual Studio to explore this in more detail.