In software development, we often need to run our program to see if it is working correctly, but why run and
inspect the results yourself when you can automate a test and have the computer verify the results?
This is one advantage to writing unit tests. A unit test is where I write some C# code to test my other C#
code in an automatic manner. Pluralsight has several courses that cover unit testing in more detail,
so in this course I'm going to stick to some brute force information to get you started.
Visual Studio provides a special project type dedicated to unit test code.
As a software developer, I can use this project to write tests for my classes and verify that they're behaving correctly.
The unit test project produces an assembly with my test code, and my test assembly typically has to reference
another assembly with the code that is being tested. For example, if I want to make sure that the GradeBook
computes the proper statistics, I'd create a new test project and write some test code where that test
project will reference the assembly with the GradeBook. That way inside of a unit test I can use the
GradeBook, I can instantiate that class, I can give it different grades and look at the output.
Let's take a look and see how this works and start writing some tests, which throughout the rest of this
course you'll learn not only how to verify the behavior of your code, but I'll show you how you can use unit
tests to experiment and learn about the C# language.
Inside of Visual Studio, before I can begin testing my GradeBook, I have to be set up with a unit testing project.
There are many ways to run unit tests on the .NET Framework. I'm going to show you one way to do this with Visual Studio.
I'm going to go to the Solution Explorer window and right-click on the Solution, the Grades Solution,
because what I want to do is add another project to the Solution.
One of the nice things about solutions in Visual Studio is they can contain multiple projects.
Each project has its own set of source code for a particular piece of the application.
I'm going to Add a New Project that will be a unit testing project.
So instead of selecting Console Application, which we did for the GradeBook, I'm going to go to this Test
node and select Unit Test Project, and let's call this project Grades.UnitTests, or perhaps let's just call
it Grades.Test. So that will be the name of my project and also the name of the assembly that this project
produces, Grades.Tests.dll. This assembly will just contain the compiled test code.
There will be a different tool, a different program that will load this library and execute the tests inside
and show me the results. And once I select OK, Visual Studio will create this project, add it to my
solution, and any time I do a build I'll be building both the Grades assembly and the Grades.Tests assembly.
Now before we even write any code, let me go to the Test menu in Visual Studio, and I'm going to say Run All the Tests.
This will launch a test runner that is included in Visual Studio, and after building both of my projects,
this test runner will go looking for tests that are in Grades.Tests.
And I can see in this Test Explorer window that popped up on the left hand side there's a single method,
TestMethod1, and the green checkmark tells me that test passed.
Of course we're not really testing any functionality yet, and before we do I just want to run through some of
the basics of a unit test. And one of the first things I'm going to do is actually drab this Test Explorer
window and dock it down here beneath my Solution Explorer just because I always prefer my code to be on the
left hand side of the screen. And now let me introduce you to some of the code that is inside of a file here.
This file is called UnitTest1.cs, and inside of here is a class, UnitTest1, and a method, TestMethod1.
We also have a new syntax feature of C#, a syntax feature that allows us to tell a test runner what methods
are tests methods, that is methods that should be executed and checked to see if they passed or failed,
and also a piece of information to identify a class that has test methods.
So this syntax with the square brackets, these are known as attributes in C#.
We're going to talk about attributes in more detail later in the course, but for now you can think of an
attribute as a piece of data that is associated with a class or a method.
You can actually associate an attribute with all sorts of different types and members in a C# application,
but again that's later in the course. For right now, just know that if you're going to write a test that the
test runner will run for you, you want to put that code inside of a method that has a TestMethod attribute
with the square brackets around it, and that method goes into a class, a public class that has this TestClass
attribute, and these attributes just sit directly on top of the language element that they are associated with.
So TestClass is associated with a class; TestMethod is associated with a method.
And what the test runner will do is just find all of your test classes, instantiate each one,
execute the methods that are inside of each one, and then determine if a method passes or fails.
How does the test runner know if a method passed or failed? Well, if there was no error that occurs inside
of test method, the test runner will assume that the test has passed.
But I can use a class that is in this namespace, Microsoft.VisualStudio.TestTools.UnitTesting.
This class is called a Assert, and I can use this Assert class to make assertions about a particular piece of
data or a particular facet of my program. And if those assertions don't hold true, they will raise an error
and fail my test. In other words, once I dot into this Assert class, I can see all sorts of methods that are
available like AreEqual, AreNotSame, AreSame, Fail, IsFalse, IsTrue, so I can try to make an assertion like
are 3 and 4 equal? And if I run all of my tests again, the Test Explorer will tell me that no I have a failing test.
I know that now because of all the red that shows up. And I can actually click on TestMethod1, and I can see
some more detail here on the right side, AreEqual failed. Expected 3, Actual 4.
That means I expected a value 3, I expected that to match the value 4, but we all know that 3 is not equal
to 4, so this test failed. And if I double-click on this method, Visual Studio will actually place the cursor
inside of that method. That way if a test fails and I don't have the file open, it's very easy to double-click
a test and go directly to the source code. If I change Assert.AreEqual where I expect a 3 and the result to
compare it to is a 3, now if I run all the tests, I am back to having a passing test.
And so the ultimate goal with my unit test will be this: I want to make sure that the GradeBook is behaving
correctly, so I want to write one or more test methods that will feed some data into the GradeBook and then
make assertions about the GradeStatistics that the GradeBook returns.
Did it find the correct high grade, the correct low grade? Did it compute the correct average?
In order to do that, I'm going to create a new test class with new test methods, and for now I'm going to get
rid of UnitTest1. This is really just sort of a sample file that Visual Studio gives you so that you can see
the proper syntax for writing a unit test. But now that we know that syntax, we can create a source code
file with a better name and better tests name inside, test names that are related to the GradeBook.
Let's do that next.