Let's write some tests to make sure that the GradeBook is computing the proper lowest grade and proper average grade.
To do this, I'm going to make a copy of ComputesHighestGrade by selecting that method, pressing Ctrl+C,
and then Ctrl+V to paste it in. Anytime you do a copy, paste operation in code, you should really take a
step back and make sure that that's the proper approach to solving a problem.
Copy and paste is duplicating code throughout the software, and that's generally something that we try to avoid.
However, inside of a unit test we often allow for duplicate code because it makes the tests a little more
explicit and clear, and that's what I'm going to do here. I'm going to duplicate a lot of code, but I am
also going to change the name of this method because now we're going to check that we compute the lowest grade properly.
I'll still add the same grades to the GradeBook, but now I want to have an assertion that 10 is result.LowestGrade.
Now I can run all tests by going the test menu or by pressing Ctrl+R and then the A key that will run all tests.
And I now have two passing tests. Let me paste a copy of ComputesHighestGrade, which I still have in my
clipboard, only this time we will check to see if we compute the average grade.
And this time I want to add some slightly different data to the GradeBook to make things a little more interesting.
So instead of adding 10 and 90, let's add the same grades that we are adding inside of Program.cs.
So I will take that code and copy and paste it inside of here. Then we can compute the statistics,
and this time I want to check the result.AverageGrade. And if I enter those results into a calculator,
the calculator will tell me that the average of those three numbers is an 85 followed by 1 and then 12 6's,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, and then a 7. Let me run all the tests again, Ctrl+R and then A,
and I now have a failing test, which will teach us an interesting lesson.
Let me click on that test, and I will see that this 85.16 number is not equal to an 85.16 number that is slightly different.
And the important lesson is that it's very difficult to make assertions about floating point numbers and say
that two numbers are going to be exactly equal because there can always be a little bit of imprecision inside
of the computer because of the way that it represents floating point numbers.
This could be a topic that we could spend a lot of time on, but let me just show you a couple different solutions.
One is you might remember there are two ways to represent a floating point number in C#.
There's the double type and there's the float type. Double is double-precision floating-point, and the float
type is single-precision floating-point. You might remember from an earlier module when I tried to assign a
number like this to a variable of type float the C# compiler wouldn't allow me to do that because by default
a number like this will be treated as a double-precision floating-point number.
And really what's happening here is I'm comparing a double-precision floating-point number to a single-
precision floating-point number, and just like I did in a previous module I could append an f to this literal
number, and now at least the C# compiler will treat that as a single-precision floating-point number and
compare it to another single-precision floating-point number. But more commonly what you want to do is this:
I don't particularly need the GradeBook to store this many digits after the decimal.
Perhaps I really only care about two digits after the decimal. And any time you compare floating-point
numbers or double-precision floating-point numbers inside of a unit test with things like AreEqual,
there's typically an option that allows you to specify are these two numbers close enough?
And you can see in this IntelliSense window when I Assert.AreEqual on types of double or of float,
I would find that inside of here also. I can specify the expected value, what the actual computed value is,
and then a delta, which allows those two numbers to vary by that delta amount.
Let me specify a delta of 0.01 and run these tests. And I'm back to three passing tests, and I now know that
the GradeBook is going to compute the proper average with the right amount of precision that I need for
whatever application that I'm building with this GradeBook.