In this module we learned that Visual Studio and the C# compiler will compile our code into an assembly.
By default the assembly name will have the same name as the project, and then we'll have a dll or exe
extension depending on if you were building a class library or a program to execute directly.
We also learned that we need more than one assembly for most applications, and we now know how to add
references to other assemblies, both .NET assemblies, as well as other assemblies in our solution.
In our solution we had to add a reference from the testing project to the grades project so that the test
could see the GradeBook. Remember we also had to mark our Grade and our GradeStatistics classes as public so
that the test project could use the GradeBook and the statistics that it computes.
So in .NET all the types we create will live in an assembly, and the classes that we've built they are one
specific type that we can create in .NET. In the next module we'll see additional types that we create and
understand two fundamental categories of types in .NET.