Reference types in C# are types created from class definitions, like the GradeBook that we created in the
second module of this course. Any time I write a class I'm creating a new reference type, and we talked a
little bit about the behavior of reference types in the second video module.
I told you that when I have a variable typed as GradeBook, which is a reference type, the variable holds a
reference or a pointer to an object. What's inside the variable is literally an address that tells the
runtime where to find the object in memory, and I can have multiple variables all pointing to the exact same
object instance, and I can have multiple objects, and I can have multiple variables pointing to all different objects.
I can even take a variable and reassign the object that it's referencing, so it points to a new object,
a different object then what it started with. Let's do some more experiments in Visual Studio to see how this works.
Let's pick up in the grade solution that we were working on in the last two modules, and I want to do a few
different experiments with the GradeBook, and before I start what I want to do is temporarily comment out
this code so that this code doesn't execute, and there's a couple different ways to comment out these multiple lines.
One is I could go to the Edit menu, I can select this command Comment Selection, that will comment out each
line of code that I have selected with the curser, and there's a hot key combination that you can use to do
that, Ctrl+K, Ctrl+C, I'll select this option, and now if I run the program nothing will happen because I
don't really have any substantial code inside of my main method, it's just going to start, and exit,
and the program's done, and that's thanks to this single line comment, which is a //.
Any where you put a // you can add text, or you can comment out code, or you can have a note about something
that is in your code. Another way to do this would be to make it a multiline comment, so first I'm going to
uncomment the selection, which is Ctrl+ KU, you can also get to that command from the Edit Advanced menu.
And now I'm going to use a /*, this is a multiline comment in C#, everything after /* is going to be
commented out and not execute until I put in a */ to end that comment.
So now that we have that code marked to not execute, let me go into the GradeBook itself, and I want to give
the GradeBook the ability to have a name so I can identify the GradeBooks with some friendly identifier,
and one easy way to do that is just to give this class a public field of type string, and let's call it Name.
I'll use an uppercase N just because public class members typically start with an uppercase letter,
whereas private class members like this grades field, it's going to start with a lowercase G.
And now that I have a name let me go into Program.cs, and what I want to do is to create two GradeBooks.
We'll call the first GradeBook g1, that's a not a great variable name, but this is just for experimental
purposes, I typically want to have a more descriptive name. And then let's create a second variable g2,
and give it a copy of what is in g1 because GradeBook is a class, and it's a reference type.
The value that is inside of that g1 variable is going to be a pointer, so I'm copying that pointer from g1
into g2, and that means if I set the name of the GradeBook through the g1 variable, and let's call it Scott's
grade book, and then I Console.write g2.Name. What I should see when I run this program by hitting Ctrl+F5 is Scott's GradeBook.
That's because I have two variables that are pointing to the exact same GradeBook object.
Now if I exit this command prompt, and I come into the program, and just before assigning name I say g1
equals another new grade book, now if I run the program when I write out g2.Name I don't have any output,
that's because there are two GradeBook objects floating around in memory, and by the time we reach this
g1.Name line of code, g1 is pointing to a different GradeBook than g2, g2 is still pointing to this original
GradeBook, which we haven't given a name. Now one way to do these types of experiments is just to write some
code inside of a console application, and run the program, and look at the output.
That can be useful, and it's a good way to learn C#, and some of the topics like we're talking about now,
reference types, how do they behave, but an even better way to do this I think is to use unit tests.
Generally you're going to write unit tests to prove the correctness of your program, and make sure it's
behaving correctly, but when I'm learning a topic like a new library, or a new API, or a new language,
I find unit tests to be an invaluable way to create some experiments, and test some hypotheses, and see if my
understanding of a particular behavior is correct. Since we already have a unit testing project that we
created in the last module, Grades.Test, let's take advantage of that, and put some code inside of here that
is really code that you can use to test yourself and experiment with the language.
I'm going to Add a New Folder to this test project, and I will give it the name Types, and I can place all of
the C# code related to my experiments with reference types inside of this folder, as well as other types that
we're going to be creating, so inside of here let me add a Class, and let's just call this ReferenceTypeTests.
I'll click Add, Visual Studio will add a class for me. Remember I want to make this a public class,
and I want to give this class the attribute TestClass, which means I need to bring in the namespace,
which is Microsoft.VisualStudio.TestTools.UnitTesting. Any this light bulb appears you can open up that
light bulb by pressing Ctrl and period. That's really handy if you want to keep your hands-on the keyboard
and not use the mouse to select the light bulb. I'm going to press Ctrl+ period, I'm going to select the
first option here by just pressing Enter, which is to add that namespace to the top of the file for me,
and now I can write a TestMethod, so first the attribute TestMethod, and this will be a public void returning
method, let's call it VariablesHoldAReference, and now let me go back to Program.cs, select this code that I
have here, and cut it out, come back into my Test, and paste it in, and really what I want to do in this Test
is just some experiments, so my first experiment will be I want to instantiate a new GradeBook, I want to
have two variables that I think are pointing to the same GradeBook, so I'll set the name through one
variable, g1, and then I want to make an assertion, I want to Assert that the following two things are equal,
I want to assert that g1's name, which I just set, is the same as g2's name because g2 is pointing to the
same object, and when I look at g2.Name I will see that the name has been set by that previous line of code,
and now back in the program I just want to clean things up a little bit, so let's get rid of our
console.write line here, and let me get rid of the comment so that we put our program back in a correct state.
I'm not interested in running the program right now, I'm more interested in running this test, so let me hit
Ctrl+R and then A, and our Test Explorer pops up, and I can see that test passed, so my understanding of
reference types seems to be working. Now what you can do inside of this Test Project is do different
experiments with different variables, and write some assertions based on what you believe should happen,
and then run the test to see if your beliefs are true. We'll continue writing some tests throughout the rest module also.