As I mentioned earlier, every type in .NET falls into one of two categories. Every time is either a
reference type or a value type. A variable that is typed as a value type does not hold a memory address or a
pointer, it holds a value itself. For example, integers and floats are value types in .NET.
If I have a variable called x1, and it's of type int, and I use it as a variable inside of a method,
if I give that variable the value 100, the value 100 is literally stored inside the memory location of variable x1.
There's no pointer here, the value is wholly inside that variable.
I can have another variable of type int, let's call it x2, and I can assign it the value 4, and that value 4
is inside the variable, this is unlike the GradeBook variables we've created, g1 and g2,
because those variables hold pointers to an object. Now why do we have these two different types?
Well value types exist because they are generally faster to allocate in memory than reference types,
that's one reason for the distinction. Creating an object is more expensive than creating a value type like
an integer, and some programs need lots of value types to exist, millions of number for example in a mathematically-oriented program.
So value types are very fast, and they are also usually small. It takes a lot less memory to store an
integer than it does to store an entire GradeBook. Many primitive types in .NET are value types,
primitive types being those low-level primitives that we can't program without, types like integers and
floating point numbers, these are small values that store themselves directly in a variable.
And one thing we'll revisit later is that value types are typically immutable, meaning you cannot change the
value of a value type. That doesn't mean I cannot change the value inside of a variable, I can always walk
up to an integer variable named x2 and give it a different value, I could change it from a 4 to a 3,
but that value 4 and that value 3, those values I cannot change, the value 4 is always the value 4,
the value 3 is always the value 3. And an obvious question at this point would be how do you know when
you're working with a value type, and how do you know when you're working with a reference type, and how do
you create your own value types, we've seen how to create reference types.
Any time we create a class like the GradeBook we're creating a reference type, but what about value types,
we'll answer these questions very soon, but first let's jump into Visual Studio, and do some more experiments.
Inside of Visual Studio we're doing some experiments with types inside of unit tests, and so far we've
written a test that says variables hold a reference, but now we know this is only true if the variable is
typed as a reference type, which is the case for GradeBook, it's a reference type.
So let's be a little more explicit with this test name, and say that GradeBookVariablesHoldAReference,
and now write a test that looks very similar, but with a value type.
I'm going to create a new test by using a code snippet, we've use d code snippets before, in this case the
code snippet is testm, I just need to type those characters, and press Tab twice, Visual Studio will generate
a test method for me, so press Tab twice, and now after inserting the snippet the name of this method is
selected by the editor, I can immediately start typing to change the name, so let's name this method IntVariablesHoldavalue.
And I want to write a test that is very similar to our other test, I want to create one variable,
let's call it x1, and we'll give it the value 100, create a second variable x2, and copy the value that is
inside of x1 into x2. We did the same thing with the GradeBook, but in the case of the GradeBook the value
that is inside the variable is a pointer, so with GradeBooks we have two variables pointing to the same object.
The question is with integers, if I make a change to x1, and give it the value 4, can I still assert that x1
and x2 are equal? Let's press Ctrl+ RA to run all the tests and find out, and the answer is no,
that test failed because x1 now holds the value 4, x2 still holds the value 100 that I copied into it.
So with the GradeBook variables I can point two variables to the same object, and then make a change to that
object through either of those variables, and the change will be visible through the other variable,
but that's not the case with value types. If I copy a different value into the x2 variable,
that's completely independent from the storage location of x1, so I don't see that change reflected here,
I would have to assert that these two are not equal, and then run the test, it should pass, which it does.
Now if you want a good exercise to test yourself and really grasp this concept of reference types versus
values types, try to figure out what would happen if I add this line of code inside of GradeBookVariablesHoldAReference.
I'm going to say just before assigning g1.Name g1 equals a new GradeBook.
What you should do is pause the video, and then think about if any other changes are required inside of this
test method to make the test pass. That is do you have to change the assert from are equal to are not equal?
And hopefully you have tried that, hopefully you came up with the correct answer.
The correct answer is that I would have to change the assert because I have assigned a new value into g1,
I have given it a pointer to a new GradeBook, a second GradeBook object.
I'm changing the name of that second GradeBook, but g2 is still pointing to the first GradeBook that I
created, therefore that first GradeBook doesn't have a name, and that assert.AreEqual g1.Name, g2.Name, that would fail.
So these are the kinds of tests and experiments that you can do inside of Visual Studio with unit tests to
really see if you are understanding some of the language concepts and features.
And now that we've seen how these two behave, let's answer those questions of how do I know I'm working with
a value type, and how do I create a value type.