One way to create a value type with C# is to create a structure using the struct keyword.
A struct definition looks just like a class definition. A struct has a name, it has an opening and a closing
curly brace, and everything inside of those braces will be a member of the structure.
You can even apply an access modifier like public or internal, really the only syntactical difference is the
keyword that's being used, struct or class, which leads to the next obvious question, when should I write a
struct, and when should I write a class. The general rule of thumb is that you want to write a class by default.
Structs are meant for special cases when you need to write an abstraction that represents a single value,
like a DateTime that is inside of the .NET Framework that represents a single value even though you can break
a DateTime down into small constituent pieces like the current hour, or the current day, or the current year,
a DateTime does represent something that we can reason about as a single value, and it's a value that
represents a point in time. Other value types in the .NET Framework, types like int, very obviously hold
only a single value, but over the years I've built many custom value types using struct, and I've done this
to represent things like complex numbers, or a point in two or three demential space, or a currency amount,
which consists of a monetary value and a currency symbol, all of those abstractions represent single values
conceptually, and the other characteristic that those value types have in common is that they are all small.
Structs do best when they contain a small amount of data because as we'll see value types get copied around in memory frequently.
A value type like int in C#, that not only requires 4 bytes of data to store, and most CPUs will copy that data
just using a single CPU cycle, but more on that later. Another way to create a value type in C# is to use the enum keyword.
An enum creates a type that will only hold specific numerical values.
An enum, which is short for enumeration, and it's a good way to create named constants in your software.
So here's a scenario, let's say we're building an application to pay employees, and we already have an employee class.
One attribute we need to tract for each employee is how they are paid, are they paid on an hourly basis,
are they salaried, are they an executive, one way to represent those categories would be to give each
category a number, so an hourly employee has a payroll type of 4, and a salaried employee has a payroll type of 2.
The problem is if we actually use those numbers in our source code they become what we call magic numbers.
You look at the source code and you see a 2, what does that represent, is that employee hourly or salaried,
I'm not sure, those are the types of things that you forget about 24 hours after you write the code.
An enum can turn those magical numbers into symbols, so instead of using the value 4 for an hourly employee,
I can use the code Payroll.Type.Hourly, so an enum isn't something that I have to instantiate to use,
I can just use the name of the enum, and then one of the members of the enum that I have defined like
.constractor, .salaried, and so forth. So in the if statement we're looking at using an employee object,
every employee object has a field named Role that is defined of type PayrollType, so instead of saying
.Role=2 or .Role=3, I can involve this enum, and the code is a little bit clear.
Defining an enum is very simple, you use the enum keyword, give the enum a name, there's an opening and
closing curly brace just like a class, but what is inside are your symbols.
Here we have Contractor, Salaried, Executive, and Hourly. By default the first entry in an enum will carry
the value 0 because behind the scenes this enum is represented as an integer value like 1, or 2, or 3.
Inside the enum you can explicitly assign values as we've done here when we say Contractor = 1.
What the C# complier will do is automatically assign the next numerical value if I don't explicitly provide
one, so Salaried would be a 2, Executive would be a 3, Hourly would be a 4, and this code we'll just use the
defaults there, but we could've explicitly overwritten that and said hourly = 128 if we wanted to.
Let's take a look at this in code.
In Visual Studio let me first show you an easy way to figure out if you're working with a reference type or a value type.
When I declare a variable like g1, which is of type GradeBook, how do I know that's a reference type?
One way to do this is to put the curse on the GradeBook symbol and use the F12 key, we've used this before,
that will take me to the source code if Visual Studio has the source code available, and when I come to the
source code for GradeBook I can see it's defined as a class, therefore this is a reference type, and g1 will hold a pointer.
What about integers? I can use the same trick here. I can press F12, integer is part of the .NET Framework,
but what Visual Studio will do is recreate the structure of that type from metadata, so this is the metadata
view we used this earlier in the course. We can see that his is part of MSCorLib.
So that's where the int type lives. Now you'll notice the actual name of this type is system.In32,
it's not int, and that's just because in C# int is a C# keyword that will give you an in32, so I could define
these variables using either the C# keyword int or the type system.in32, it's all going to come out the same
in the end, those two are completely equivalent. I prefer to use the C# keyword int, but you can see here
that int, AKA an in32, it is a struct, therefore an int is a value type.
If I looked at the DateTime type in .NET I would see it as also a struct, and this metadata view, by the way,
can be very useful if you're trying to figure out what something can do for you, I can look at this in32
type, and I can see that I can convert an int to a string, I can compare integer values, I can parse an
integer out of a string, we will look at some of those features later in the course.
For right now I'd also like to show you how to write or use an enum that's built-in to the .NET Framework,
so let me create a new test method. This time what we're going to be experimenting with is StringComparisons.
So first I'll declare a variable, let's call it name1, and it's going to point to value Scott with an uppercase S.
So is string a value type or a reference type in .NET? If I press F12 I can see clearly that string is a
reference type, don't let anyone ever tell you anything different, however string is a little bit magical,
and we'll talk about that later in this module. So string is a reference type, name1 points to the string Scott.
Let me also declare name 2, and I want this to point to scott, but without an uppercase S, and now what I'd
like to do is do a StringComparison that will tell me these two strings are equivalent, so I need to do a
StringComparison that ignores the case of the individual characters, so an uppercase S should be equivalent
to a lowercase S. Let me declare another variable of type bool, so we can hold the value true or false.
What is bool by the way? Bool, also a value type, it's a struct. I'm going to say that result =
String.Equals, and I want to compare name1 and name 2, and there's an optional third parameter here where I
can specify the type of StringComparison to do, and StringComparison is an enum, so if I say
StringComparison., Visual Studio will show me the various StringComparisions I can do.
I can compare strings and take into effect the CurrentCulture, my CurrentCulture is set up for English.
I can also ask for InvariantCulture, so it doesn't matter whether my machine is set up for English,
or Spanish, or French, or Norwegian, and I'm going to select this option, InvariantCultureIgnoreCase.
And I want to assert it IsTrue this result because if I'm ignoring the case when I compare these two strings
I should get a true out, and I now have six passing tests, so that has worked.
Let's press F12 on StringComparison, and go to the metadata view, and here I can see how that enum is defined.
I'm using StringComparison.InvarientCultureIgnoreCase, which holds the value 3, that would actually be the
value that's passed around behind the scenes, but if I try to put a 3 in here you'll notice I do get the red
underline, which indicates there is an error, so even though that underlying value is a 3, I cannot pass the
integer value 3 into this method. The C# complier wants to see something that is one of these StringComparison values.
That's another benefit of using strong typing and using enums instead of just magic numbers.
And speaking of passing parameters to a method, another topic that we want to make that we're comfortable
with is how these different types, these reference types or value types, how they behave when we pass them to another method.