Understanding the difference between how reference types and value types behave becomes extremely important
when you write methods and pass parameters to a method. In C# the default is to pass parameters by value.
This means when you call a method that takes a parameter, by default the value in the variable you pass will
be copied into the variable that is a parameter to the method, and what you pass is always a copy unless you
add some additional keywords, which we will talk about, but you hardly ever want to use these keywords,
you want to use the default of pass by value, and that means for reference types you are passing a copy of a
reference, a copy of the pointer that is inside the variable, and when I pass a value type to a method,
a value type like an int, or a double float, or DateTime, I am passing a copy of the value, a copy of the
value that is inside the variable. So if I have a method that takes a GradeBook parameter, and I pass the
method of variable from my code, the method gets a copy of the pointer to a GradeBook, so both the calling
code and the method that is being called, they will both have pointers to the exact same object, and this has
profound implications for what happens inside the method, and what changes I can see when a method exits and
returns control to the caller. Let's take a look in Visual Studio.
Inside of our testing project we're really branching out beyond just reference type tests, so let's rename
our test class to just TypeTests. The name of a test class really doesn't matter except in the output of the
test explorer, and what I want to do now is write a couple test methods that I can use to explore the
difference between value types and reference types when it comes to calling methods.
The truth is there really is no difference, we're always passing something by value, but behavior may appear
differently, let's just take a look. Let me create another test method with a code snippet, and let's name
this method ReferenceTypesPassByValue, and what I want inside of here is code that is similar to some of the
other code that we've written. I want to create a new GradeBook, and I want to have two variables that point
to that GradeBook, so book2 will equal book1, what is this line of code doing, it's copying the reference
that is inside of book1 into book2, so now I have two variables both pointing to the same object,
and now let's call a method. I'm going to write a private method, GiveBookAName.
Since this method is private and doesn't have a test method attribute, it's not going to be a method that the
test runner tries to invoke to see if something is going to pass or fail, and simply a method that I can use
inside of my tests, and this method I want it to take a GradeBook parameter, and I want it to set the name of
the GradeBook, so book.Name = A GradeBook, and so back in my test method I want to invoke this method,
GiveBookAName, I want to pass in book2, and then I want to write an assertion that will pass that will look
at book1's name, and I'm going to paste in that string A GradeBook. We're going to see if book1.Name is
equal to a GradeBook, Ctrl+ RA to run all the tests, and I now have seven passing tests, so I can see that
test worked because when I invoke GiveBookAName, the value inside of book2 is copied into the parameter book,
and that value is a pointer, so there is a period of time during the execution of these tests where I have
three variables that are pointing to the same GradeBook object, book1, book2, and this parameter book,
and any changes that I make to the GradeBook through any of those variables, they will be visible if I look
at that object through any of the other variables. Now let's try a similar experiment, but with value types.
So let me create a test method, we'll call it ValueTypesPassedByValue, and in this method I want to just try
some things with a simple integer value, so let's say that x = 46, and again let me create a private method,
let's say that we'll increment a number that is passed in, so this method expects an integer parameter,
we can call it the number, and all I will do inside of here is say number = number + 1.
Another way to write that in C# is to say number += 1, so that's a way of saying take this value, add 1 to
it, and assign it back to the variable. And now the question is inside of this test method is I invoke
IncrementNumber, and I pass in x, should I assert that x is a 46 or a 47, let's say that we expect a 46 to be
the value inside of x, I will run all the tests, and that is also one of my passing tests.
So what is happening here is that I take this 46 that is inside of x, it's being copied into number when I
invoke method, but since this is a copy of that value I can make any changes that I want with this number variable.
I can add 1, subtract 1, divide by 3, multiple by 6, it really doesn't matter what I do to this number inside of here.
The changes I make are only visible inside of the code that is inside of IncrementNumber, it just has a copy
of that integer value, there's nothing I can do with number that could make a change that would be visible
from the code inside of ValueTypesPassByValue, and if that's a little bit confusing that's okay,
it takes some time for this to sink in, and that's one of the reasons that I wanted you to set up a unit test
project so you could explore some different scenarios with PassByValue, and write some tests, and see what
tests pass, and what tests fail, and become more comfortable with this behavior, but one thing that might
make this a little bit more clear is this, the only reason that I can call GiveBookAName, and see changes to
A GradeBook object from outside of this method is because I am working with a reference type, and I have a
reference to an object, and I'm making to the estate of some object, and that change is visible because
there's three different variables that can all hold a pointer to that same object, but just like with the
integer experiment above, there's no change that I can make to this book variable itself that would change
the value that is inside of book1 or book2. So for example, down here if I said book = new GradeBook,
this is not going to change the pointer or the reference inside of book2, it's only going to change the value
that is stored inside of this book variable inside of GiveBookAName, so that particular variable will be
pointing to a new GradeBook, but the variables that are back in the calling method, book1 and book2,
they won't be changed at all, and if I run this test I will find I have a failing test because we will no
longer be setting the name of this GradeBook that we created, we're creating a second GradeBook and setting its name.
So the way to think about this really is that both tests demonstrate that C# uses PassByValue, and in both
cases when I pass a parameter to a method, there's no way that the method that I call can make a change to
the value that I hold inside of my variable, but if what I'm holding is a pointer to an object,
that method can always make changes to an object that are visible to me as a caller.
Now there is a way in C# to make changes to the variable, the value of that variable when I invoke a method,
it's a rare scenario, but let's talk about that next.