In C# there are two keywords that can change this
default behavior of PassByValue, these two keywords are ref and out.
I'm going to show you how they work, but I will say that in 15 years of developing with C# I rarely if ever use these keywords.
There's a few special methods that Microsoft provides in the .NET Framework where I have to use these
keywords, but I rarely if ever use these keywords in methods and classes that I build.
I will cover these key words for those of you that want to get a complete picture of the C# language,
but feel free to skip this clip and move to the next one if this something that doesn't interest you.
So the two keywords are ref and out. Let's go back to the situation where I am saying book = new GradeBook
inside of GiveBookAName, and I've already demonstrated that this test will fail now because when I change the
value inside of book that does not change the value inside of book2, therefore book2 still pointing to the
original GradeBook, and I'm only changing the name on a new GradeBook that is created here inside of
GiveBookAName, but all that can change if I use on of these two keywords, ref or out.
These keywords go in front of the type for the parameter, and this is the ref keyword, and the way to think
about it now is what I'm receiving inside of the book parameter is a reference to the variable in the calling
code, and there's a couple observations to make. For those of you with a computer science background, yes,
you can think of book as a pointer to a pointer, but the syntax that I use inside of the method doesn't have to change.
If I assign a new value to this parameter you can think of that value being written into the book2 variable,
but the way I access the GradeBook doesn't change, I can still just say book., and I get to any instance
member of that object. The next observation to make is that I have a complier error.
When the C# complier see you're invoking a method that has a ref parameter, it also wants to see the ref
keyword in front of the parameter when you invoke the method. That just makes it very explicit when you're
calling another method, that you are passing this variable by reference, and it's quite possible that the
method you are calling can change the underlying value inside of book2.
So I'm about to run the tests, and I want you to take a guess whether the test will pass or fail.
Let me give you a little bit of a hint, the assertion right now is still looking at book1.Name, so if I run
the test, the test is still failing because when I say book = new GradeBook down here, yes, I'm writing a new
value into book2, but that doesn't influence book1, I don't have a reference into that variable, I have a
reference into book2, so book1 is still pointing to the original GradeBook, but book2 now, let's write an
assertion against that, and just to make this clearer perhaps, let's get rid of the ref keyword for just a second.
I'm going to run all the tests, that test should still fail because in this scenario when I say book = new
GradeBook, we're back into the scenario that we previously looked at where I am writing a new value into this
book parameter, but there's nothing I can do here that can change the value that is inside of book2,
so book2 is still pointing to the original GradeBook. Let's change this back to ref, and I'm writing the
assertion against book2.Name, let's run all the tests, and the tests now passes because when I say book = new
GradeBook inside of GiveBookAName, I can think of this book as pointing to the new GradeBook,
and because this is a by ref parameter I've also changed where book2 is pointing, so it's pointing to that new GradeBook also.
The ref keyword, I can also use this against value types, so we've already seen if I call IncrementNumber on
x, there's nothing I can do inside of IncrementNumber that will actually change the value that is inside of
x, but that's all different if I use the ref keyword. If I use the ref keyword, and I also use it here where
I am invoking the method, I can think of number as a reference to this variable location, the x,
so any changes that I make to that value like incrementing the number, that change will be reflected inside
of x, so Ctrl+ RA to run the tests, I expected a 46, but now the actual is 47, I did increment that number.
Let's change the assert, run all the tests, and now we have a passing test.
Let me show you the other keyword, the out keyword that also changes the behavior of PassByValue, and the out
keyword is pretty much identical to ref. Let me just change both the method and the calling of that method
to use the out keyword, and here we will see what the real difference is between ref and out, with out the C#
complier assumes that you are creating an output here. Most methods produce an output by returning a value,
but when you use the out keyword, the semantics are that you are producing an output through this parameter,
and one of the things the C# complier wants to see is a definite assignment to that parameter.
Right now the error is Use of unassigned out parameter number, that's because in order to add 1 to number,
and say number += 1, I first have to read the number, and then add 1 to it, but the C# complier is saying
since this is an output I cannot guarantee that the caller gave you an initialized value that you can use,
and so for this scenario I have to use the ref keyword if I want to increment an existing number,
and with ref the initialization rules are just on the other side of the fence.
So with the ref keyword if I did not have a definite assignment to the variable x, now I would get an error
in this method that I'm using an unassigned local variable. So with the ref keyword the C# complier will
make sure that you initialize a variable before you call a method.
If I have the out parameter here I wouldn't need this initialization statement, I could just say int x,
and invoke a method that passes x as an out parameter. And that's the story with the ref and out keywords.
Again these are keywords that I rarely use, there's usually a better way to design a method than by taking a
ref or an out parameter, but hopefully I've given you enough information if you do encounter one of those
keywords you'll know what to do, and you can always explore and experiment with unit tests like this to make
sure that you understand the behavior correctly.