One special behavior that I need to point out about value types is that value types are typically immutable,
which means they cannot change, and certainly the value types that Microsoft provides as primitives for us to
work with from the .NET Framewrk, those value types are immutable, and that means that once you create a
value you cannot change the value. That doesn't mean that the value stored in a variable cannot change.
We call them variables because the data inside can vary, but the actual value of the value type cannot change.
So for example you cannot change the value of the integer value 4, that seems obvious, but it also means that
once you've constructed a DateTime, which is a value type, that particular value cannot change.
So with this in mind I want to cover two common errors that new C# developers frequently run into,
one error with a DateTime value type, and one error with a string type.
Once you construct a DataTime, and yes, you can use the new operator, you can construct a DateTime,
and set that DateTime value to August 11, of the year 2002, which is what the code on the screen is doing.
That's because the DateTime constructor takes the year, the month, and the day.
Once I create this value I cannot change it, I can assign a different value into that date variable even
though the DateTime exposes members like AddDays, which makes it look like I can add one day to an existing
DateTime value, but this code has a problem because AddDays will never change the underlying DateTime value.
Instead what AddDays will do is return a new DateTime instance, so I need to assign the return value of
AddDays into a variable if I really want to capture the date. The string type in .NET also has these qualities.
What's interesting about string is that string is a reference type, and as I said before, don't let anyone
tell you that string is not a reference type. When working with strings your variables will be a reference
that point to a sequence of characters, and that makes it easy to pass strings around to different methods
because we pass a reference instead of copying the entire value of the string, and that's good because
strings can contain millions of characters and can be quite large.
A string is a reference type then, but it behaves like a value type in many ways because a string is immutable.
One of the methods on a string is a Trim method. What Trim will do is remove the leading or trailing white
space from a string, so the space characters before it and after the value Scott should be removed,
but Trim does not modify the string that I am pointing to, instead Trim will create a new string with the
characters removed, and return that new string. If all I do is just call Trim, and I don't assign the return
value of that method call to a variable, I've lost all the work that the Trim method performed, and so the
code on the screen is all wrong, don't use it, instead use the code that I'll show you now.
Inside of Visual Studio let's experiment with the code that was just on the slide, so first I will write a
new test method, this test method will test how to add days to a DateTime.
So first I will need a DateTime variable, let's just call it date, and I could assign to that variable
DateTime.Now, we've seen that earlier in the course, that will give me the current time as this program is
executing, but instead let's use a specific date. I can do that using the new keyword, and there is a
constructor for DateTime where I can pass in the year, let's say 2015, and then the month, let's just use
January, and then the day of the month, let's just use the first day, and there's also constructors that
would allow me to construct that day with a specific time during the day, but let's go with that value,
and now say DateTime.AddDays1, and like I say it's very easy to think that now you have a DateTime that
represents January 2, but if I write an assert, and I try to assert that the following two things are equal,
the value 2, and date.Day, I will find this test will fail. Before I do that I'll just point out that
there's all sorts of ways to look at various different pieces of the date, I could look at the specific hour,
or the specific millisecond, but I just want to look at the day, and if I run the test the failing test will
tell me that I expected a 2, but the actual value is 1, so Date.Day is still a 1, and that's because AddDays
will construct a new DateTime, so let me assign that new DateTime into the date variable, and run the test
again, and now we have a passing test. Next let's try something with a string, so another test method,
and let's test how to uppercase a string. So if I have a string variable, let's call it name, and I point it
to the string scott, with all lowercase characters, and yes, I do point it to that string value because if I
press F12 on string I do see that it is a class defined inside of MSCorLib, and you'll notice the class name
is actually uppercase S, it just so happens that once again C# provides a magic keyword, string with a
lowercase letter, that will map to that stystem.stringtype, so the two are equivalent.
C# is a case sensitive language, so if I didn't have that keyword in C# I would have to stay String uppercase
S, but now that we know that let's try to do something with our name.
Ultimately what I want to do is invoke a ToUpper method, which is one of many methods on the string type that
looks like it would change the underlying string, so you can Trim a string, you can Trim from the start,
or Trim just from the end. You can say ToUpper, ToLower, but if I write an assertion here, and try to assert
that the value I expect is SCOTT, all uppercase, and compare that to the actual value, which is the value
in name, if I run this test I will find that it fails because even though string is a reference type,
it behaves very much like a value type, and I can see that I expected an all uppercase SCOTT, but I actually
got an all lowercase scott, and that's because all of these methods like Trim, and ToUpper, and ToLower,
they don't modify the string that I'm pointing to, instead they create a new string, and return that string
from the method, so I really need to capture that by assigning a reference to that new string back into my
name variable, and once I do that, and I run all the tests I should find that this passes, which it does,
and hopefully this will save you some time in the future. Always remember when working with a value type
that the value type might be immutable, but methods you see on that value type might be methods that return a
new value or a new instance, and not change the underlying value, and that rule also applies to string,
which behaves like a value type.