Polymorphism is the third pillar of object-oriented programming, and if you know a little bit about the Greek
language, which I don't, you'd know that poly stands for many, and morph stands for shape, and thus we're
talking about the concept of many shapes. That's a good description for the behavior that we can achieve with C#.
I can have a variable of type GradeBook, and I can point to objects with different shapes, so objects with
different types, as long as all those objects inherit from or are a GradeBook, then it's legal.
So my GradeBook variable can point to a GradeBook, but it can also point to a ThrowAwayGradeBook because
again, another way to think about inheritance is to think about is a relationships.
We say that a ThrowAwayGradeBook is a GradeBook, it derives from GradeBook, GradeBook is a base class,
and any time you have an inheritance relationship you can have a variable typed as a base class that points
to an object derived from that base class. I cannot have a variable typed as string that holds an integer
value because those two types have no inheritance relationship, but I can declare a variable typed as object
and point it to anything, a string, an integer, a date time, a GradeBook, because System.Object is the
ultimate base class for anything and everything in .NET. Everything in .NET ultimately derives from
System.Object, so if you declare a class and do not explicitly declare a base class for that class,
the base class is System.Object, just like the code on the screen is being very explicit in saying the class A
inherits from object. I could leave the :object off and have the same result.
And class B inherits from class A, which inherits from Object. So an instance of B is an A and is an object.
There's also a keyword in C# to work with System.Object, and that's just the word object with a lowercase O.
Now in this code, both class A and class B have a DoWork method, and just like with the GradeBooks that we're
working with, we want these two methods to behave differently.
Now currently we have a ThrowAwayGradeBook, but we assigned that object to a GradeBook variable,
and when I call ComputeStatistics, we saw that we're invoking the ComputeStatistics method in the GradeBook,
not the ThrowAwayGradeBook, and that's because the C# compiler without any other information, is going to
choose the method to invoke based on the type of the variable. If I define a method or a property with a
virtual keyword, then the C# compiler will generate code to invoke that method by looking at the type of
object it's working against at runtime. Without the virtual keyword the method we invoke is determined by
the type of variable that we're invoking the method through. It's the virtual keyword that gives us
polymorphism, because now, I can have a variable that points to different objects, and when I invoke methods
or properties on those objects, they can all behave differently.
Classes that inherit from class A can override that DoWork to behave differently.
Let's get a concrete example with our GradeBook.
Currently in the GradeBook project we are not achieving polymorphism.
We're not achieving polymorphism because ComputeStatistics in my GradeBook class does not use a virtual
keyword, and thus, when the C# compiler sees a call to ComputeStatistics through a variable typed as
GradeBook, the C# compiler will determine the method to call based on the type of this variable.
So it sees GradeBook.ComputeStatistics, it's going to invoke ComputeStatistics, the one that is defined
inside of GradeBook.cs. Now let's do a little bit of an experiment.
Let's temporarily say that WriteResults has to take an object of type ThrowAwayGradeBook, which means I also
need to type this variable as ThrowAwayGradeBook because WriteResults will no longer accept just a GradeBook,
it has to have a more specific type, the ThrowAwayGradeBook, and now if I run the program, I can see I call
into ThrowAwayGradeBook: :ComputeStatistics, which calls into GradeBook: :ComputeStatistics, and now the
average is up to a 90.25 which is an A, we've thrown away the lowest grade, which is what we wanted to do.
But I'd like to achieve the same behavior using polymorphism, I'd like to achieve the same behavior leaving
this variable typed as GradeBook, and having WriteResults take an object that is just a GradeBook,
because with the magic of polymorphism I can implement WriteResults to take a GradeBook and have many
different types of GradeBooks and have those objects behave differently without me doing any additional work
inside of WriteResults, or tying myself to a specific type of GradeBook, like the ThrowAwayGradeBook.
In fact, I'm even going to take this line of code and press Ctrl+., and tell Visual Studio that I want to
extract this into a new method. I'm going to call this method CreateGradeBook, and although it might not
make a lot of sense here in a simple application like we have with the GradeBook, but there are many times in
software where you want the flexibility of having something created for you via a factory class,
or a provider, or some sort of infrastructure that's in your application, you just want something to be
created for you, know that it has some type like a GradeBook type, that you don't ultimately want to know
exactly what type you're working with. Is it a regular GradeBook, is it a ThrowAwayGradeBook, really all the
rest of the code that I have inside of Program.cs doesn't care, so I want to work with variables of type
GradeBook, but have polymorphic behavior when I invoke methods like ComputeStatistics, and that's when I have
to come into GradeBook.cs and use the virtual keyword, because now when the C# compiler sees me invoke
ComputeStatistics through a variable typed as GradeBook, it's no longer going to use the type of variable to
figure out which method to call, instead it's going to use the type of object, the type that it sees at runtime.
So if it sees ultimately that that GradeBook is a ThrowAwayGradeBook it will go looking to see if the
ThrowAwayGradeBook overrides ComputeStatistics. And this doesn't mean that I hide or replace the
ComputeStatistics method that is in the GradeBook, I can still access that method using
base.ComputeStatistics, it just means that if someone does invoke ComputeStatistics, I have the ability,
if we're really working with a ThrowAwayGradeBook to change the behavior of what's going to happen,
in this case invoke my method that I've implemented for ComputeStatistics, instead of the method defined in GradeBook.
And just to go back and talk about what was on the slide GradeBook, I haven't defined a base class for
GradeBook, but technically GradeBook does inherit from System.Object, and that's why inside of Program.cs,
any time I'm using IntelliSense against GradeBook, I can see methods that I haven't defined in the GradeBook
methods like get GetHashCode, GetType, ToString, those are all methods that are defined on System.Object,
and those are all methods that I can override. If I just type override in Visual Studio and press space,
Visual Studio is smart enough to figure out which methods that I have my inheritance chain that are virtual
that I can override. So if I wanted ToString to behave differently, I can override that method,
and provide my own custom implementation of what will happen if someone says book.ToString.
But now we're working with variables of type GradeBook, but GradeBook has a virtual method, ComputeStatistics,
and ThrowAwayGradeBook, which inherits from GradeBook, it's going to override that behavior, I should be able
to achieve polymorphic behavior when I say book.ComputeStatistics.
I'm not going to know exactly what happens at this point at compile time, I don't know what ComputeStatistics
will be invoked, because the method that is invoked will depend of the type of object that is passed in here,
not the type of variable, so Ctrl+F5, and I can see, even though I'm working with a variable of type
GradeBook, I am calling ThrowAwayGradeBook, and the lowest grade is an 89.5, which means the low grade has
been thrown away, and the letter grade is an A.