Building an abstract class is one way to define a type to achieve polymorphism, but another approach is to
define an interface. An interface definition uses the interface keyword, and an interface is a type in the .NET Framework.
Just like the class, struct, and delegate keywords define types, so does interface.
An interface is special because it can never contain any implementation details.
When you define an interface you're defining an API for an object, that is any object that implements an
interface is guaranteed to have the members an interface describes.
The code snippet on the screen if for IWindow, and it's a common naming convention to define interface types
with a leading capital I. That's how all the interfaces and the .NET Framework are defined.
So any object that implements IWindow must have a title property that is both readable and writeable,
it also must have a draw method that takes no parameters and returns void, and it must have an Open method,
also a no parameters and returns void. In some ways an interface is like an abstract type,
because in order to create a concrete class that implements this interface, I must implement those three members.
But there is one huge difference between an abstract class and interface.
When I define a class, I can only inherit from a single base class, but I can implement as many interfaces as I like.
I can inherit 1 interface, or 10. I can also inherit from a base class N, implement 10 interfaces, as long as
I have all the interface members defined. So the interface is the ultimate abstraction,
because an interface allows you to define the API your software needs without defining any of the
implementation details, and because any class or struct inherit from any interface, interfaces are extremely flexible.
People will occasionally ask me if they should be using abstract base classes or interfaces,
and I generally favor interfaces. That's just because over the years I've never looked at an interface and
said oh, I wish that was an abstract class. But I have looked at an abstract class and said,
oh, I wish that was an interface, because abstract classes can be a bit rigid, and make for a complicated
inheritance tree. So I prefer interfaces, but we can always debate this.
Let me show you some interfaces in code.
In the Grades project if I really do have to work with a wide variety of different types of GradeBooks
and GradeTrackers, I might decide that I want to work with an interface definition instead of an abstract base class.
So instead of a GradeTracker type, I would like an IGradeTracker, where IGradeTracker is an interface that
defines a programming API so I can add grades and ComputeStatistics.
In Visual Studio if I put the cursor on IGradeTracker and press Ctrl+., Visual Studio will give me an option to
generate an interface IGradeTracker in a new file, that's the option I'm going to select, so I press Enter.
And now in the project I have an IGradeTracker.cs, it's an interface that currently doesn't define any
members, so you'll notice inside of Program.cs, I'm going to have a number of compiler errors, let me go
ahead and make some changes so that CreateGradeBook returns something that implements IGradeTracker,
and WriteResults takes an IGradeTracker, so does SaveGrades, so does AddGrades, also GetBookName,
and that should be all of the changes that I need. Of course currently since this interface does not define
any members, I have no ability to WriteGrades, or AddGrades, or do anything useful with an IGradeTracker,
so let me borrow some of the code from GradeTracker. I'm going to take these first three lines and paste
them into my interface definition. Now inside of an interface, I cannot use an access modifier, so I cannot
say that a particular method like AddGrade is public, or protected, or private, and that's because when
someone has an object that is an instance of IGradeTracker, AddGrade has to be available, and there's no
sense in hiding AddGrade or explicitly saying in the interface definition that it has to be public.
Also these methods are implicitly virtual because they're part of an interface, so I do not need to the
abstract keyword. And all I'm left with now are these three members, AddGrade, ComputeStatistics,
and WriteGrades, and once again I do need to bring in the System.IO namespace for TextWriter.
And now I have a choice, I can have GradeTracker implement IGradeTracker, I can have GradeBook implement
IGradeTracker, the way you implement an interface is to use a colon, and list the interface name that you
want here, so this GradeTracker is now an IGradeTracker, and it's providing those members that IGradeTracker
demands, even if they are abstract members, so I'm satisfying the constraint to this interface.
But of course what's great about implementing an interface, or inheriting from an interface,
is I can also choose a base class that I want to inherit from. And if you do want to derive from a specific
class in addition to implementing an interface, the class that you're inheriting from, that has to come first
in this list, so I can say object, IGradeTracker, but really no one ever clutters up their code by
explicitly saying they inherit from System.Object, that's always implicit, so I'm going to leave that piece off.
Now back in Program.cs, I'm still going to have at least one error, because my interface doesn't say anything
about this object having a property name. And the C# compiler says, you're passing me an IGradeTracker,
but an object that implements this interface isn't guaranteed to have a name property, so it's giving me an error message.
I will also need to go my IGradeTracker, and say that anything that implements this interface needs to have a
Name property that you can read and write. And now I have an inheritance hierarchy where even my
ThrowAwayGradeBook is an IGradeTracker, because ThrowAwayGradeBook inherits from a class, which inherits from
a class, which implements this interface IGradeTracker. And now I should be able to build and run the
program, and it's still behaving the same, but my program is working through an interface, and that again
increases the flexibility of the software. Previously when I was working with the GradeTracker, I could get
back any type of object, but it ultimately had to be something that derived from this abstract class GradeTracker.
By working with an interface I can work with an even wider variety of objects, objects whose class definition
doesn't even inherit from a GradeTracker or a GradeBook. The only guarantee that I need is that the object
that's being created and worked with here implements this interface IGradeTracker.