Now that we know about interfaces, I wanted to tell you that .NET is full of many useful interface definitions.
Because the interfaces are flexible, and because C# allows you to implement multiple interfaces on a type,
you'll see interfaces in use to provide many low-level and essential features.
For example, one interface we've already used is IDisposible. You might remember in the last module when
we talked about exception handling, I showed you that we can have a using statement in C# to automatically close
a file, even if there is an exception. The interface that the using statement looks for is IDisposible.
Any object that implements IDisposible is an object that needs some help cleaning up.
So it opens files, or database connections, or network connections, and in order to keep this system running
in a good state, we want to make sure these resources are properly cleaned up, that's the purpose of IDisposible.
IDisposible forces an object to have a dispose method that you can call directly, or indirectly through a
using statement, and dispose will clean up resources. Another interface is IEnumerable.
An object that implements this interface is an object that you can enumerate, that is you can use it as a
collection in a foreach statement. There's also INotifyPropertyChanged.
This is an interface you'll implement if you get into desktop XAML development, it requires you to raise an
event when a property changes its value, much like we're doing in the GradeBook when we raise a NameChangedEvent.
The INotifyPropertyChanged interface defines an event that a UI framework can listen to and know when to
update the data on the screen. And then there are lots of little interfaces, interfaces like IComparable,
IEquatable, these interfaces allow you to compare objects, or check to see if two objects are equal.
And these types of interfaces are commonly used by collections, like the sorted list collection,
because the sorted list can use methods defined by IComparable to compare objects and keep them in sorted order.
Let's take a look.
Inside of the WriteResults method let's say that instead of just writing the statistical results to the
screen, I also want the ability to write out the individual grades.
And ideally what I'd like to be able to do is a foreach statement.
So I'd like to be able to say, foreach grade that is in the book, or the tracker, I'd like to be able to
Console.WriteLine that grade. But currently the C# compiler is going to give me an error because it knows
that book is not something that I can use the foreach statement against.
Technically what's happening is an object that implements IGradeTracker is not guaranteed to have a public
method GetEnumerator. At the lowest level that's all an object needs, just a method called GetEnumerator.
But it's more common if you have a type that you explicitly want to make enumerable, you will say that that
type inherits from the IEnumerable interface. So if I swing over to IGradeTracker, I can say that an
IGradeTracker is something that is also IEnumerable, and IEnumerable is an interface that is defined in the
System.Collections namespace, so I need to have a using statement for System.Collections.
And now back in Program.cs, I will have no problem using a foreach statement with an IGradeTracker,
because anything that isn't IGradeTracker is guaranteed to have GetEnumerator.
But just because I have that interface listed on IGradeTracker doesn't mean I'm completely finished,
because now what the C# complier will tell me if I do a build, is that I don't have any implementation of IEnumerable.
So GradeTracker, our abstract base class, it has to implement IGradeTracker, it does not define the method GetEnumerator.
And where does GetEnumerator come from? Well remember when I'm implementing an interface, I have to provide
a definition for all of the members that that interface defines.
So IGradeTracker defines four members, IEnumerable, if I go to the definition for that by pressing F12,
it's a very simple interface that only defines one method that you have to have, it's a method called
GetEnumerator, and GetEnumerator has to return an object that implements another interface, an IEnumerator.
Something that implements that interface knows how to step through a collection one object at a time.
And this is an extremely powerful interface definition, because you can hide all sorts of work behind an
IEnumerable and an IEnumerator. So what I currently need to do is I need to guarantee the GradeTracker
implements this interface, so I need to have a method, a public method, that returns an IEnumerator, and it's called GetEnumerator.
But the problem is a GradeTracker will not know how to enumerate the grades that it holds.
So first, IEnumerator, that's also an interface defined in the System.Collections namespace,
I'm going to bring that namespace in. And the problem is now I do not how to implement this method inside of
an abstract class GradeTracker. So I will also mark this member as abstract.
I don't know how to implement GetEnumerator, because from the perspective of GradeTracker, I don't know where
the grades are stored, are they in memory in a list? Are they in a database? Are they behind a web service call?
I don't know, but I need to have this member here to satisfy the constraint that I am in IGradeTracker,
I'll just mark this member as abstract, so whoever derives from this class will have to provide an implementation.
Now before we do that, I just want to show that a GradeTracker could implement as many interfaces as it likes.
So it could derive from a specific base class, like object, and then I could go on and say this also
implements IGradeTracker, and IDisposible, and IClonable, I could list all sorts of interfaces,
or course, I would have to have the members that these interfaces define, but I'm just trying to show you the
syntax for how this would work, I can list interfaces, as many I need, and just separate them with commas.
So let's go back to being just IGradeTracker, and of course if I do a Build now, my problem is pushed up one class.
Now if go to the GradeBook, well I've said that GradeBook is a concrete type, it's not using the abstract
keyword here, and therefore I need to provide an implementation for GetEnumerator.
And fortunately, a list is something that's also IEnumerable, so all the collection classes in .NET,
they implement the IEnumerable interface, and so I could provide an override for GetEnumerator,
that simply calls into Grades, and returns Grades.GetEnumerator.
That's the easiest way to implement this logic, and so now, inside of Program.cs, when I say foreach across
an IGradeTracker, I don't know if I'll be getting those numbers back out of a list, or a database, or a web
service call, again that's the great advantage to using interfaces, you can build very powerful abstractions,
and hide all sorts of complexity behind simple polymorphism. If I run the program, I am now printing out the
grades, as well as the statistics, as well as the letter grade.
And hopefully that will demonstrate some of the flexibilities that interfaces can provide.