If you enjoyed this course you might enjoy a few of my other courses.
I do suggest you watch these to get the complete C# fundamentals experience.
First is my C# Generics course, at least watch a couple modules here because generics are an incredibly
important feature of the C# language. We just didn't have time to cover generics in this course with the
amount of detail they deserve, although we did use a generic type when we declared a list to store our grades.
Another important set of features in the C# language are the LINQ features, where LINQ stands for Language Integrated Query.
It sounds like something data related, but in truth, LINQ added a number of wonderful features to the C#
language, features like extension methods and lambda expressions, and you don't have the full C# experience
until you see these features. And finally there is my C# Fundamentals Part 2 course, which is C# programming
paradigms, this course includes some additional material on not just object-oriented programming,
but also functional programming, and what I call language-oriented programming with C#.
I also offer some tips, tricks, and rules to live by as a C# developer.