Conditional branching is something that we're already using in this course, but we really haven't stopped to
dig into the details of the if statement, which is one way to branch execution.
And by branching, I mean we have some code where we want to go in one of two directions, it's like getting
into the branches of a tree where one branch sprouts out to the left, and one branch to the right,
which direction do we go? That's what an if statement can do. The if statement selects a statement for
execution based on the value of some Boolean expression. So, in the first if statement on the screen,
if age is less than or equal to a 2, that's a Boolean expression that we'll return true or false.
If the expression returns true, the if statement will execute the statement that immediately follows the if.
If the expression is false, we'll skip that statement. Notice that I don't need to use curly braces to
surround the call to ServeMilk, but it is a considered a good coding style to use curly braces,
because curly braces make the code easier to maintain and a little more readable.
The curly braces are required if I want to execute multiple statements when the expression returns true.
I need to use the curly braces to create a block of code, and that block can enclose multiple method
invocations, multiple statements, inside of the if. Without the curly braces, I will only execute the
statement that immediately follows the if. Now if the first expression inside of an if statement returns
false, let's say that age is a 10, we will not invoke ServeMilk, and instead we'll jump to the next if
statement, because this code snippet includes else statements. It's like saying I need to check to see if
the age is less than or equal to 2, if it's not, then I need to go and check to see if the age is less than 21.
And if both of the tasks were to return false, we will fall into the final else statement and invoke a method ServeDrink.
You don't need to include an else statement after every if that you write, but you can have as many else ifs
as you want after an if test. Notice that the curly braces are not required around ServeDrink either because
it's just a single statement, but again I believe it makes the code a little more readable.
And speaking of readability, it's also possible to nest if statements.
So any code that I would place where the comment is in the middle of the second code snippet,
that code will only execute if the age variable is less than or equal to 2 and the name variable is equal to Scott.
You have to be careful nesting too many statements together like this, because the code can become hard to
read when you have if statements inside of if statements inside of if statements.
Closely related to the if statement is the conditional operator.
It's also sometimes referred to as the ternary operator because it comes in three pieces.
The first piece is an expression that needs to return true or false, so age greater than 20.
And then the conditional operator will return one of two values based on the evaluation of that expression.
If the expression returns true, we'll return the value that is on the left-hand side of the colon.
And if the expression returns false, we'll return the value on the right-hand side of the colon.
So, for example, if the age variable contained the value 19, the expression will return false,
and the string pass would be assigned the value, nopass. This conditional operator is sometimes useful when
you just need a really quick conditional check to assign one of two different values.
You can write the exact same logic with an if statement, but with a conditional statement there's fewer
characters to type. You do have to be careful with the conditional operator because again,
sometimes it can make the code difficult to read. Let's take a look at branching in our Grade Book.
Let's take a look at branching using the Grades project that we've been working on throughout the course.
The first thing I'm going to do, just to simplify some of the output is remove some of the code that we used
to experiment with events. So I'm going to remove everything related to the Grade Book name,
and changing the name, and that includes writing out the name, and also this event handler that we had to
print out some output when the Grade Book name changed. Again just trying to simplify the program and I'm
trying to make all the changes to the code here in the video so you can follow along.
I can also get rid of one of these WriteResults if I remove that cast to an int that we placed here in the
previous module, and we did that just see an example of method overloading, but I'll give you another example
of method overloading here in just a bit. Here's what I'm thinking we could do, I want the GradeStatistics
class to compute a letter grade. What is a letter grade? Well here in the States when I was growing up,
my school teachers would grade all of my assignments, quizzes, and tests on a scale of 0 to 100,
where 100 was a perfect score, and then periodically they would take all my scores and compute an average,
and from that average, compute a letter grade. It was the letter grade that was sent home to my parents to
tell them how I was doing in school. And when I was growing up the letter grades were A, B, C, D, and F.
An A meant that you were doing wonderfully in a class, it was the best letter grade you could get.
And then there was a B, and then there was a C, a C was considered average, then there was a D,
and then there was an F. An F meant that you were failing a class.
And I think I can get the Grade Book statistics to compute this logic just using some simple if else statements.
So let's add another property to GradeStatistics, this is something the statistics can do all on their own,
given an average grade. So let's create a property called LetterGrade.
For this property, I'm only going to use a get accessor, that effectively makes this a read-only property,
no one will be able to assign to it, which is just what I want, I want the letter grade to be computed from
the average grade, there's reason to set the letter grade. And the letter grades work like this,
if your average grade was greater than or equal to a 90, then that was a letter grade of A.
And you might want to use something like math.round, so that a student with a score of 89.9 would also have
an A, but I'll leave that as an exercise for you to try out. But now if the average grade is less than 90,
I need to handle that situation too, so let me write an else if.
Else if the AverageGrade is greater than or equal to 80, that would be a letter grade of a B.
Now, generally speaking, I try to maintain a coding style where I only have a single return statement inside
of a method or a property. That's not always possible, but it does make the code sometimes easier to read.
I'm going to reach that goal, I'm going to try to do that by declaring a local variable result,
and in this case not even initialize that because I expect to initialize it in the logic that is inside of
this property, and instead of immediately returning, let me just say result = A, and result = B,
and at the bottom whatever we have computed for result, that is what we will return.
Currently we have an error because the C# compiler is smart enough to realize that you might be returning an
unassigned local variable. If the average grade right now is lower than an 80, then we never make an
assignment to result, and the C# compiler won't let us get away with that.
So let's continue writing out some of our logic. If the letter grade is less than an 80, we won't branch in
to assign a result of A, and we won't branch in to assign a result of B, so now we will have to check if the
average grade is greater than a 70, and if so the result is a C.
And notice one thing that I don't have to do here is I don't have to check that the average grade is greater
than 70 and the average grade is less than 80. Technically that is the rule to get a letter grade of C,
your average grade has to be greater than or equal to 70, or less than 80, but the way the if else statements
work, I know that this test I don't really need this, because if the average grade was greater than 80 we
already would have assigned a result here and skipped over this else if statement, we would never evaluate this.
We'll need one more else if to check for a letter grade of D, which would be an average grade greater than or
equal to 60, in that case, the letter grade is a D, and then finally, if I haven't branched into any of
those if statements, then I know that the average grade is less than a 60, and the result should be a failing
letter grade, a letter grade of F. And if I come back into the program, let's write out the letter grade,
let's try to do a WriteResult of Grade, with stats.LetterGrade, and this is one of those situations where the
C# compiler says, oh you're passing a string here, I don't see a version of WriteResult that takes a string,
so let me copy this method and paste it in here, and create a version a WriteResult that takes two strings,
one is the description, one is the result. I do not need to format result a floating point number,
so let me take off the :F2 here, and run the program, and I can see that the average grade is an 85 and the
letter grade is a B, so I think my logic is working correctly. Of course I should write a unit test to make
sure, but again I'll leave that as an exercise for you to try.