The C# language also includes a switch statement. What the switch statement allows you to do is branch the
execution of a program to a set of statements that are inside of a case label, which you create with the keyword case.
The switch statement does this by matching the value inside the switch against the values that you specify in
each case label. These values for each case statement, they must be compile-time constants,
and we can see in the code on the screen, we're checking a variable to see if the name is equal to one of the
string literals, Scott or Alex. If the name is Scott, we execute the method ServeSoda, and then we break out
of the switch, that is we jump to the line of code following the switch.
So we only execute the code inside of a single case. You can have multiple statements and multiple lines of
code inside of a case, but you also must have a break statement in each case, that's a little bit different
form other languages like C++ where you can fall through from one case to the next.
Now if the value you are switching on does not match any of the values in the case statements,
then the default path can be chosen, but you don't need to have a default label, so that's entirely optional.
Let's take a look in code.
Back in the Grades project, it might be useful to provide a textual description of the letter grade,
that is a grade of A should produce text like excellent, while a grade of F should produce text like failing.
This type of logic I could also add to GradeStatistics, and I could do this as another property.
So in addition to the LetterGrade property, here is another public property of type string,
let's call it Description, and just like LetterGrade, this will have only a get accessor.
And inside of here, I could look at the average grade, but I could also look at the letter grade.
I could say okay, if the letter grade is an A, let's produce this text, and if it's a B let's produce this
text, and that's the type of logic I could do with if else statements, but since we're looking at switch,
let's do a switch on LetterGrade instead. A switch statement is very much like a series of if else if
statements, and what I can do case the letter grade is the string A, let's execute the following code.
And what I want to do ultimately is compute some result, just like I did with LetterGrade,
and then return that result at the bottom of the property. So when we have a capital A, let's say that the
result = Excellent, and then you can think about this as else, if I have the sting B, the result would be
equal to Good, or we could say Above Average, and notice I have a compiler error right now because it's
illegal to fall through from one case label to another. And there's a couple ways to solve that error,
but by far the most common approach is to use a break statement, and what the break statement will do is
allow me to execute as many lines of code as I want inside of that case label, but once I hit the break
statement, I'll be jumping out of the switch. And if we have a letter grade of B we can then break,
of course a C, the result for a C would be Average, and then we break.
We also need to handle the D case, and for the result there we could say Below average, and then break,
and now I have a choice, I could either write another case statement and say, case letter grade is an F,
or I could have a default label, in which case if the letter grade is anything but an A, B, C, or D,
we will end up inside of here, and I can say the result is Failing, and once again I will still need a break.
Let's try this out in the program. Instead of writing out the text Grade, let's write out stats.Description.
I will run this program, and I can see that a B is a Good grade, so my switch statement appears to be working.
So switch is the type of logic that you could also implement using if and else if statements,
but note that I would not be able to implement LetterGrade using a switch statement.
In a switch statement I cannot write an expression like AverageGrade greater than or equal to 90,
all I'd be able to do is switch on AverageGrade, and have a case when AverageGrade is 90 exactly.
So switch statements, not so useful for evaluating ranges, but sometimes useful for replacing if else if statements.