There are four different statements for iterating in the C# language, iterating being a fancy term for
looping over code and executing a block of code repeatedly. Typically you want to loop because you want to
execute some code for each item in a collection, like printing out each number in an array of integers,
and one statement we've already used is the foreach statement. This is where you use the foreach keyword,
and declare a variable before the keyword in. The code on the screen has a variable named value,
and I want to point out that this value variable, it's only available inside the block of code for the
foreach loop, so once you exit the foreach loop and you've moved beyond that closing curly brace you can no
longer access the variable named value. The code inside this loop, it will see each number in the array,
and the variable value will hold each item once. So the first time through the loop we'll see the value 2,
and the last time through the loop we see the value 100. This ages variable, by the way, it is an array of
integers and we are initializing that variable using a collection initializer syntax in C#.
This is where we just place objects or values between curly braces on the right-hand side of an assignment,
and the C# compiler is smart enough to say yes, I can create an array from those values.
Another looping construct in C# is the for statement. You can think of the for statement as being more
explicit about the starting and ending conditions for looping, because with foreach you basically say,
loop once for each item, but with a for loop, you have to say I'm going to start at 0 and I'm going to go to
the number 4, because I know I have an array that has 5 items inside.
To operate at this lower level, the for statement includes three pieces of information,
there's the initializer, the condition, and the iterator. This is the same as the for loop in C, C++,
Java, JavaScript, and many other languages. The for statement begins execution by executing any statements
that are specified in the initializer, and these statements are only executed once, no matter how many times
you're looping, that only executes once, then before any statements are executed inside of this for loop,
the condition is evaluated, the condition appears after the first semicolon.
The condition is always a Boolean expression that has to return true of false.
If the expression returns false, then we do not execute anything inside of the for loop, and we stop looping
and continue with the next statement after the for statement.
But if the condition evaluates to true, we'll execute the statements that are inside of the for statement,
that is everything inside the curly braces, and for that reason you could say that a for loop will execute
0 or more times because the program does test this condition before the first pass through the loop,
and if it returns false on the first test, we don't execute any code inside, but then after each execution of
the code inside, the iterator executes. In this case the iterator is incrementing the variable i,
and then we come back and check the condition, if it returns true, we execute again.
So the iterator is typically used to increment or decrement some sort of index variable, and I'm using a
variable named i, i is short for index, that's a fairly common convention in C# programming.
The while statement, this is another way to loop 0 or more times in a C# application.
In this case the while statement evaluates an expression, and if that expression returns true,
the statements inside the while loop will execute. Once the while loop is finished executing,
the condition is evaluated again, and at some point, that condition should return false, unless you're trying
to write an infinite loop, and infinite loops can be useful in some situations, but when that expression
returns false, that's when we finish executing the while loop. And closely related to the while loop is the do while loop.
The do while loop always executes one or more times, you're guaranteed to execute the code inside of here at
least once, because the primary difference between a while and a do while is that in a do while the condition
is checked after the code inside of the statement executes, so you're guaranteed to have control pass through
a do while loop at least once. Let's see an example in the Grade project.
Inside of the Grades project I'd like to give the GradeBook a new feature, I'd like to be able to walk up to
any GradeBook object, and tell it to loop through the available grades that is has and write them to the
screen, or write them to some destination. I'd like there to be a little bit of flexibility.
For example, I'd like to be able to say something like, GradeBook, please write out the grades,
and then pass in a parameter that will allow me to change destinations.
Maybe I want it to be on the screen, maybe I want it to be in a file, and fortunately, the .NET Framework
contains some abstractions that will allow me to do that. For example if I call WriteGrades,
which is a method we still have to implement, but I pass in a static member of the Console class,
which is the Out property, what that will do is send an object into that WriteGrades method that the
GradeBook can use to write out to the screen. The GradeBook doesn't know it's the screen,
but Console.Out, it represents the output stream that goes to this console window, to the screen.
We'll see the type of that parameter in just a second. Let me use Visual Studio to generate this method on
the GradeBook, I can do that by placing the cursor on WriteGrades and pressing Ctrl., you can see the
drop-down option here is to generate a method, GradeBook.WriteGrades, that's exactly what I wanted to do,
so I'll press Enter to take that selection, and now if I come over into the GradeBook I should be able to
find that method in this class, it is right here. Let's make it a public method, let's get rid of this line
of code that is inside the method, we'll replace it with something more useful, and let me change the name of
this parameter to destination. But before I do, why is there an @ sign here?
The @ sign is here because out is reserved keyword in C#, it's not legal to have a parameter named out,
but anytime you want to have a parameter or variable name that has the same name as a C# keyword,
you can escape that name using the @ sign. For example, I could also say @class if I wanted this parameter to be called class.
But I generally avoid names that require an @ sign, let's call this destination.
You'll see this destination is of type TextWriter, and this is a useful abstraction in the .NET Framework
because I can write information into a TextWriter, and ultimately I don't know if that's going to a file,
or to the console, or over the network, it just so happens that this particular TextWriter is going to be
Console.Out so it will send output to the screen, but we'll see later some of the flexibility that this
abstraction gives me. Now we've already seen how to use a foreach loop, so let's try using a for loop.
There's a code snippet where if I just type for and press Tab, Tab, Visual Studio will generate the
skeleton of for loop, it's going to do that by having an initializer i that starts at 0.
Before we enter the loop each time we'll check to make sure that i less than some value,
that's something we're going to have to change, and each time after the loop executes, we will add 1 to i using i++.
So I want to loop from i = 0 to i is less than the number of grades in my list.
Fortunately this private variable, grades, it has a Count property, and quite often if you're going to write
a for loop against a collection, that collection will be a list which has a Count property,
or an array which has a Length property, and you can use those properties in the conditions for your for loop.
And now what I can do, is use my destination to write a line, which is grades, and I'm going to index into
grades using that i variable to pull out a specific grade, the first grade will be index 0,
the last item will essentially be index grades.Count -1. If I run the program, then we're printing out the
3 grades that we entered into the GradeBook, 91, 89.5, 75. Very good.
What if we wanted to do them in reverse order? Well then I could start at grades.Count, and I could go and
loop while i is greater than 0, and each time through the loop I would decrement i, or subtract one from i.
And now because I'm starting this index at grades.Count, I just have to make sure that I subtract 1 from i
when I index in to the Grades list. That way I don't try to index in to the Grades list with a value of
3 when Grades only contains 3 items, so now we get the grades in reverse order, 75, 89.5, 91.
So the for loop is quite flexible, I prefer to use foreach when I can, and I would certainly use a foreach in this
scenario, and I could even use a while loop, like the while loop that we saw on the slide.
What I certainly wouldn't want to do is use a do while loop, at least not without writing some additional
code, because a do while loop always executes once, and there's a possibility someone might invoke
WriteGrades when there are no grades in the GradeBook, in which case we would never want to enter into a
loop that tried to index into the grades, that would create a runtime error.
We'll be talking more about runtime errors in this module, but next, let's talk about some statements that
allow us to jump around in code.