C# includes a number of keywords that allow you to unconditionally jump to some target.
These keywords include break, continue, goto, return, and throw.
We've already seen break, we know that we can use break inside the case label of a switch statement,
but you can also use a break inside of a while loop, a do loop, a for loop, or a foreach loop,
to break out of a loop and stop looping. For example, here is a foreach statement that's going to loop
through some collection of integers, and inside of the code if the age variable holds the value 21,
we're going to break out of this loop. So if age is equal to 21, even if there are more items left on that
collection, we're going to stop execution of the foreach loop and continue execution on the statement that
is after the foreach statement. The continue statement in similar, except that instead of breaking out of
the foreach statement, we're going to skip executing any code after the continue statement and go to the next
iteration of a loop. So in the code if we encounter an age value equal to 2, we're going to continue the
loop, we're not going to execute anything that follows, and we're not going to jump out of the foreach statement.
Essentially the continue statement starts the next iteration, and you can use it again inside of a while,
a do while, a for, or a foreach statement. And then there is a goto statement in C#.
You can use the goto statement to jump to another statement that is marked by a label.
So in this version of the foreach loop, if we encounter age equal to 2, we're going to jump execution down to
the label with the name of skip, and jump over any code that was in between.
I do have to say in over 25 years of programming with various languages, I've never had to use a goto
statement, and most programmers avoid goto at all costs, because it does make a program harder to follow.
The return statement, this is something that we've also used in the demos of this course,
but I do want to point out that you can use a return statement with a void method.
So typically what we've done is, we'd have a method that has to return a string or an integer or some type of
object like a GradeBook Statistics object, and we used a return statement to return the value of some variable.
But it is legal to use return when you have a void method, you're just not allowed to pass a value back to the caller.
In that case you just have the return statement. So in this foreach loop, if we encounter an age equal to
21, we are not only going to break out of the loop, we're going to jump out of the method itself.
So if there was any additional code before we reach the end of the method, that code wouldn't execute.
The last jumping statement that we need to cover is the throw statement, which it means it's time to talk about exceptions.