The throw keyword in C# is used to raise an exception. An exception is a signal that an error condition
exists, and as the name would imply, an exception should only be raised in exceptional circumstances,
that is, you shouldn't use exceptions to change the normal program flow.
Use exceptions when your software finds itself in a position where it cannot move forward.
Exceptions are what happens when you have a bad input value, or the program is out of memory,
or a network is not available for communication. Those are the types of situations that may require
exceptions, but not always. When you throw an exception, you are throwing an object, this is why we say
exception handling is type safe because every exception with C# is going to be of a known type,
and the compiler can help you handle exceptions. We also say that working with exceptions is structured,
because you can set up blocks of code to handle exceptions, meaning you can structure your program to
anticipate certain exceptions, and try to recover from those error conditions.
The reason we use a throw keyword, is you can picture your software throwing some error object,
and the error object is going to start travelling back through the program until it is either stopped by an
exception handler, which is a piece of code that tries to recover from an exception,
or if there are no exception handlers, we have what we call an unhandled exception.
With .NET an unhandled exception will terminate your program, which sounds terrible, but in reality it's
usually better to shut down a program that has an unhandled error than it is to let the program continue
because the program might be in a bad state after an error occurs, and it could save corrupt data,
it's much better to fail. In this code snippet, we're checking to see if the age value is equal to 21,
and if it is, we'll throw a new ArgumentException. So you can see that an exception object will have a type definition.
In this case ArgumentException is a built-in class in the .NET Framework, and we need to create a new
instance of that ArgumentException, and when we do, the constructor allows us to pass in a description so we
can give some additional information about this error. Now if it is a common occurrence that age could be
equal to 21, it's probably not something that you want to generate an exception for,
exceptions should be for exceptional circumstances. Let's take a look in our program.
Inside of the Grades project, you might remember that we gave the GradeBook a Name property in a previous
module, and then the logic for the setter of that property, we added some validation checks to make sure that
the incoming NewName value was not going to be null or empty. And currently, if a caller tries to set the
name of a GradeBook to something that is null or empty, we silently ignore that assignment.
What I'd like to do now is create an error condition so that if a caller tries to set the name to an invalid
value, we will create an error condition in this program, we'll do that by throwing an exception.
And to do this, I'm going to restructure the setter just a bit, I'm going to remove this if check,
actually I'm going to cut it out with Ctrl+X, and remove the curly braces that made that a block of code,
now I'm going to press Ctrl+K, followed by Ctrl+D, that allows Visual Studio to reformat that code,
and we've removed the indentation that was there, we don't need that indentation any longer.
And now what I want to do is have an if check, but this time I will remove the not operator,
so this time I want to check if string.IsNullOrEmpty, and I can do that just by going right the string
class and invoking the static method, I can also do that through the string keyword that is in C#,
and now if value is null or empty, I want to throw a new exception.
But what exception should I throw? There are many built-in exceptions in the .NET Framework,
you can also create your own custom exception classes. A class that represents an exception that you can
throw, it always ends with the word Exception, that is in the class name.
And you can see if I just start tying Exception, the IntelliSense window will filter things out so I'm only
looking at exception types. And just based on the few namespaces that we have imported right now,
you can see there are many built-in exceptions. These exceptions include everything from a
DirectoryNotFoundException, to a DivideByZeroException, and there's also some built-in argument exceptions,
so there's ArgumentNullException, I could throw this exception if someone passes me an argument and that
argument is null and I cannot work with a null value. There's also a slightly more generic
ArgumentException, which is just a way of saying something is wrong with one of the arguments.
And in the constructor for the particular type of exception, there's an overload of the constructor that
allows me to pass in a more explicit message, so I could say, Name cannot be null or empty.
This would be one way to do it, and let me hit Ctrl+K, Ctrl+D again to do some reformatting of the code,
and let's go back to program.cs, and try to set the book's name to a null value.
So using the null keyword in C#, run the program with Ctrl+F5, and I can see that the program has crashed
with an unhandled exception, a System.ArgumentException, Name cannot be null or empty.
Notice that this error information includes a line of code where this error occurred, and in order for
someone to help track down the error and why this occurred, there's a full stack trace printed.
So what is a stack? As a program is executing and you call a method, that calls another method,
that calls another method, there's a data structure being built internally that we call a stack,
and with each method that you call, something is pushed onto the stack.
You can imagine almost like a stack of papers on someone's desk, every time we call a method,
we write the method name down on a piece of paper, and add it to that stack, and every time a method finishes
executing and it returns, we pull a piece of paper off the stack and we can look at that next sheet and know
what method we came from, who was the caller, and go back there.
A stack trace is showing you how execution arrived at this point in code where the unhandled error occurred.
And it's telling us that the exception was thrown from line 53 of GradeBook.cs, but that's not really helpful
when you're trying to track down a problem. What's really helpful is usually something further up the stack,
and what's further up the stack is Program.cs line 14, and if I close the program and go to line 14,
I am on the line of code that is really responsible for creating this error condition because this is the
line of code that passed an illegal value. Reading the stack traces that come out in an error message can
quite often help you try to locate the piece of code that started all the problems and led to an unhandled error.
So now we've seen that an unhandled exception can terminate an application, but let's look at the other side
of exceptions now and see how they can handle an exception, and prevent a program from crashing.