In a C# application you have the option of trying to handle an exception using a try catch statement.
A try block is the try keyword followed by some curly braces, and inside the curly braces are the statements
that you want to execute that might throw an exception. The try block can be followed up by one or more catch statements.
In this case we have one catch statement. If ComputeStatistics were to throw an exception, the runtime will
go looking for the closest matching catch statement, and by matching I mean that if ComputeStatistics were to
throw a FailNotFoundException, the catch statement that I have here will not catch that exception,
because that's a different exception type. This catch statement is looking for a DivideByZeroException.
And when I say that the runtime looks for the closest matching type, I mean that the runtime is going to look
for the handler with the right type of exception that is nearest to the point where the exception occurred.
That doesn't mean closest in the source code, that means closest in the execution of the program.
So if ComputeStatistics were to throw an exception, but it already has an exception handler for a
DivideByZeroException inside of that method, then this catch statement would not get the opportunity to
catch the error, the exception would already be handled. Let's take a look in the program.
Inside of my program I know that if I set book.Name equal to null, that will cause the program to crash,
and it would be easy enough for me to fix this problem just by giving the GradeBook some name with characters inside.
But what if I didn't want to hard code a string, what if I needed to prompt the user for a GradeBook
name, and I'll ask them please Enter a name, and then instead of a hardcoded string I use Console.ReadLine.
Now I'm in a situation where I don't know when the program runs what value we'll try to write into book.Name,
but I do know if the user gives me an invalid value, that will cause the program to crash.
Now, ideally what would happen is, I would not assign Console.ReadLine directly into book.Name,
instead, I'd save the value into a variable, perform some validation, and only set book.Name if have a valid
value, and I might try to do that inside of a loop and continue to prompt the user to enter a name,
as long as they're giving me an invalid value. But I'll leave that as an exercise for you to try,
and instead what I want to do is just use some exception handling to prevent an application crash.
So if I know book.Name will throw an exception that could crash the program, I might use a try catch statement.
Inside of the try I can have as many lines of code inside of here as I want, so I could even include the
Console.WriteLine, and if any exceptions emerge from any of the statements that are inside of the try,
I will have the opportunity to catch those exceptions using a catch statement.
With a catch statement I first have to describe the type of exception that I want to catch,
in this case it would be an ArgumentException, and then I can optionally provide a variable where the runtime
will store the exception object that was thrown. So when book.Name does throw an ArgumentException,
I will capture a reference to that object inside of this variable ex.
And now I could Console.WriteLine and tell the user that they entered an invalid value,
I could also look inside of that exception object, and I can see there are properties like Message,
what is the message associated with the exception, even a StackTrace, so I could print out a stack trace if I
wanted the user to see things about method names and line numbers and .cs files.
But let's just print out a Message, and now run the program with Ctrl+F5, when prompted to enter a name,
I can just press the Enter key that will enter in an empty value, but now I'm catching the exception,
I'm displaying the text Name cannot be null or empty, that's the exception object's Message property,
and now the program can continue to run, there are no unhandled exceptions, and I print out the grades and the statistics.
When we get to our next demo, we'll see what dangerous things can happen when I actually enter a valid name.