You can follow a try block with multiple catch statements. This is known as chaining the catch statements.
And even though we have multiple catch statements, only one of these catch blocks can execute after an
exception is thrown from inside of the try block. The catch blocks will be evaluated from top to bottom,
and the first one that specifies a matching exception type will be the catch block that executes.
And that's why when you chain blocks like this, you want to include the most specific exception types first.
And by specific I mean this, DivideByZeroException is specific exception type, but all exception types in
.NET derive or inherit from a base exception class with the name just Exception.
And we're going to talk more about inheritance and derivation in the next module, for now you can just know
that this exception type is special that will catch nearly every type of exception that can be thrown in a C#
application, there's just a few very special and very catastrophic exceptions that will always crash a
program, you cannot catch them. But because I can catch nearly everything with this exception type,
I want to include that catch statement after other catch statements, like a catch statement for
DivideByZeroException. If the exception was on the top I'd never get the DivideByZeroException because that
is also an instance of an exception type. Let's look at chaining in the demo.
Back in Visual Studio let's run the application with the debugger by pressing F5, and now let me enter a name
for the GradeBook, and when I press Enter the program generates an unhandled exception.
The debugger will automatically stop on a line of code that generates an unhandled exception,
and in this case we stopped on the line of code where we are invoking the NameChanged event.
And you can see the exception is a NullReferenceException. And what's happened here is that we have
declared this public event, NameChanged, but this event currently has the value null because there are no
subscribers to this event. And as I've said before, if you try to invoke or use a variable that contains a
null reference, you can end up with this NullReferenceException, and currently this exception is unhandled,
and this is something to be careful of when you're using events, if no one has subscribed to an event,
the event will be null, and that can create a NullReferenceException.
This is an unhandled exception because we do not have an exception handler for a NullReferenceException,
just an ArgumentException, but let's stop debugging and see if we can prevent the program from crashing.
Now the ideal solution to this problem is to make sure that that event is not null before trying to use that
NameChanged event. But before we do that, I wanted to use this scenario to show you how you can also catch
a NullReferenceException, I can also name this variable ex because it is in a different scope than the ex
variable for my ArgumentException, that only exists for the first catch block, and here in the second catch
block I can now do a Console.WriteLine, and perhaps just provide a generic error message here like Something
went wrong, and you'll notice in this case I'm not even using that variable ex, well the variable is
optional, this is a way of telling the C# compiler I want to catch a NullReferenceException, but then I don't
need a reference to that exception object, my code has all the logic and data that it needs, I don't need the variable.
Now if I run the program, this time I'll run it with Ctrl+F5 without the debugger, enter in some name,
and we now get the exception message Something went wrong. I could also try to catch Exception,
and let's try to do that first. If I catch Exception, so not ArgumentException but just Exception,
both ArgumentException and NullReferenceException, they both are of this exception type, and you can see I
even get a complier error that says A previous catch clause already catches all exceptions of this type or a super type.
So again more on super types and inheritance in the next module, but if I wanted to catch all exceptions,
that catch clause would have to come here at the end. And I could also just use my existing block,
and instead of catching a NullReferenceException just catch all exceptions and write out Something went wrong.
But I will caution you that that is potentially dangerous, because you won't know if you're catching an
exception that is related to security settings, or memory settings, or something went wrong in the input
output system, when you catch exception you're catching everything, and we might be allowing the program to
continue execution when what really should have let happen is let that exception go unhandled and terminate the program.
But when I catch exception I can still enter a name and get that message Something went wrong.
And like I say, the proper way to handle this is inside of the GradeBook, and it would actually be rather
important to make sure that NameChanged is not a null value before I try to invoke it, and I could do that by
adding an additional if statement here, we've talked about nested ifs earlier in this module, or I could also
add an additional condition to this Boolean expression. So I could say name is not equal to the existing
value, and NameChanged is not equal to null, that way both of those conditions have to be true before we go
out and instantiate NameChangedEventArgs and raise this event. And with logic in place, I shouldn't need to
catch a NullReferenceException, I should just be able to run the program, enter in a name, and the program continues normally.
We're not listening for the NameChanged event, but that's okay, we didn't need any logic in the program
to do any sort of processing when that event occurs.