After a try statement you can optionally include a finally statement.
The finally statement allows you to specify a block of code that is always going to execute even if there's
an exception inside of the try block. So the finally code executes when there is an exception,
and when there is no exception, and that makes the finally block a good place to add finalization code,
that is, code that will clean up resources that you might have acquired previously.
In .NET we talk about managed resources, but really the only resource being managed by the .NET runtime is memory.
The runtime knows what memory you are using and what memory you are no longer using and it cleans things up for you.
There are other resources you'll probably need in an application, resources like a data file,
or a network socket, or a database connection, and when you're working with these resources it's important
to close, or release, or free these resources when you're finished.
Otherwise you can leave behind corrupt data or run out of these resources.
In this sample we're opening up a file on disk, and we want to make sure it's closed even if there's an
exception that's thrown. We can do that with a try finally by putting a file.Close call inside of the
finally block, and although I didn't show it in this example, you can also have one or more catch statements
in here that try to catch exceptions. Many of the classes in .NET that represent unmanaged resources,
that is resources that you have to explicitly close, they all implement a special interface known as IDisposible.
We'll talk more about interfaces in the next module too, for now just know that if an object has
a disposed method that you can see in IntelliSense, chances are the object is a disposable object,
and you can implement the try finally logic in a cleaner way with a using statement.
This is not a using statement for namespaces like we saw earlier, this is a using statement that will make
sure an object is properly disposed and resources are freed, even if there is an exception.
So in the code snippet I'm using two FileStreams, and these FileStreams will be available throughout the code
that is inside of the curly braces beneath the using statements, and once we reach the bottom curly brace,
the C# compiler will generate code to make that these FileStreams are properly disposed and they're properly closed.
That makes sure that all the data that we might have written to a file will be flushed out to disk,
and also these files won't be locked and prevent someone else from opening up the file.
Let's take a closer look in code.
Let's work with a file in the Grades project. What I'd like to do is have the GradeBook write the grades
that it stores into a text file, and we already have a WriteGrades method on the GradeBook that allows the
caller to set the destination using a parameter. In this case the destination is the Console,
so all my program really needs to do is swap Console.Out with an object that will write to a file instead.
And this can be fairly easy with the .NET Framework. There is a file class in the .NET Framework,
it's in the System.IO namespace, so I'm going to type in file and press Ctrl., that will bring up the action
menu that allows me to select this top entry, which says please add a using statement for System.IO at the top of this file.
And now on this file class, there's number of static methods that allow me to easily create, and append,
and delete files from the file system. I'm going to choose the method CreateText, I need to give this method
a string parameter that tells the framework the name of the file that I want to create, and let's call that
file Grades.Text, and you can see this method returns an object that is of type StreamWriter, and it turns
out that a StreamWriter is compatible with a TextWriter that the WriteGrades methods expects.
So if I press F12 to go that method definition, you'll remember we created this method taking a TextWriter,
and a StreamWriter is a type of TextWriter. So let me save the return from File.CreateText into a new
variable of type StreamWriter, let's call it outputFile, and now what I should be able to do is pass
outputFile into the WriteGrades method, and let's try it out by running the program with Ctrl+F5.
I'll need to give the GradeBook a name, let's just give it the name Z, and now I no longer see the grades
being written to the console, but let's go out and check our Grades.Text file.
Since I didn't specify a full path when I did File.CreateText, this file should be created in the same
directory where the program is executing, and one easy way to get to that directory is right-click on the
Grades project, say Open Folder in File Explorer, and then I can navigate to the folder where the actual
assembly lives, so that's the bin, Debug folder, and it's inside of here where I can see a text document,
grades.Text, let's open that up and you can see that it is empty.
Now this file may not always be empty, it might depend on other things that you're doing in your program,
or if you're doing anything with the debugger, but what's happened here is I have written information into
a stream, and you have to be a little bit careful with any type of stream, whether it's a FileStream or a
NetworkStream, streams have a tendency to buffer information that you write into them, and if you don't
properly flush that stream, or close that stream, or dispose that stream, there's a chance your program could
exit without the information ever arriving at the actual destination.
So this StreamWriter, it does have a Close method, and let's just see what happens if I explicitly invoke
this Close method, run the program again, give the GradeBook a simple name, and now come back out to the
folder, and open up this text file, and I can see the grades did successfully arrive inside of the text file,
so that's good, but typically you don't want to write your code in this style when you're writing a real C# application.
Anytime you're working with input and output, there's always a chance for an exception, and you might say
well, what types of exceptions? For example, you might be wondering what types of exceptions could
File.CreateText throw? And one way to answer that question is to go to the documentation.
Since the File class is part of the .NET Framework, I can go to msdn.microsoft.com,
the Microsoft Developer Network, and I should be able to find documentation of File.Create.
So let me do a search for File.CreateText, and here is that method as the first result in the search list,
and as part of the documentation for this method, there will be a list of exceptions that this method could
potentially throw. And you can see there might be an UnauthorizedAccessException,
or an ArgumentException if I pass an invalid path. The path could also be too long, Windows has a limitation
on the maximum length of a path and file name. I could also be trying to create this file in a directory
that doesn't exist. So all sorts of things could go wrong. And ideally what I would do, is I would use this
StreamWriter inside of a try, catch, finally construct, where inside of the finally I would do something like,
outputFile.Close to make sure that no matter what goes wrong inside of creating the file or writing the
grades, I'll always be closing this file that I'm creating. But the try and the catch is only useful if I
actually want to do some sort of exception handling and process exceptions.
And so an alternative approach to making sure this output file is always closed, is to wrap this StreamWriter
with a using statement. The using statement is essentially saying I'm going to be using this unmanaged
resource, this StreamWriter in the following block of code. So I will use curly braces to contain all the
code that's going to be using that resource, and behind the scenes what the C# complier will do is
essentially set up a try finally to make sure that if there are any exceptions inside of this block of code,
then it will always dispose of this output file. And you can see in the IntelliSense window that there is
both a Close method and a Dispose method. And any time you see a Dispose method that's a good indication that
you would be able to use this object in a using statement. And many classes in .NET will offer both a
Dispose method and then some sort of explicit Close method, and you can think of them as synonyms for one
another, and they both ultimately achieve the same effect which is to make sure this unmanaged resources
released, and closed, and flushed properly. And since I now have outputFile wrapped with a using statement,
I no longer need to explicitly invoke close or dispose, that's going to happen for me.
And if book.WriteGrades does throw an exception, it will go unhandled and crash the program, but that's okay,
I'm still going to make that these resources are cleaned up. If CreateText throws an exception,
that will also be an unhandled exception, I have no try catch block here, and in that situation we'll have to
assume that the .NET Framework is properly cleaning things up, because if CreateText throws an exception,
I'm not going to get an outputFile object back, I'm not going to get a StreamWriter.
So this code should be a little more robust now, and I should be able to still run the program, enter a name
for my GradeBook, and come out to the Grades.Text file, and see that it's populated.
And any time you're working with an object and you see there is a dispose method, you'll probably want to
consider if you should be using a using statement or not. Now there's one more thing that I want to do to
this program before we leave, and that's just clean a few things up because we have various bits of code
scattered around this main method doing all sorts of different things, and to me the method just feels messy.
So one thing I would like to do is highlight the lines of code that try to achieve a specific goal,
like getting the name for a GradeBook, and refactor these bits into individual methods that have a name.
And one easy way to do that is to select the code, and then press Ctrl., the only option that pops up here
is an ExtractMethod option. This is part of the built-in refactoring tools in Visual Studio,
and if I just select this option, Visual Studio will create that method for me and I can name this method
now, I could name it something like GetBookName, and when I press Enter, Visual Studio will apply changes
throughout my source code, I now have a method that I can call GetBookName, which will contain the code that
was previously inside of the main method. Let's do this a few more times, let's also use ExtractMethod on
these three lines of code, because what these three lines of code are doing are really adding grades to the
GradeBook, then, I'm using a few lines of code here to save the grades to the file system, and finally at the
end I'm going to extract a method to write the results. And now to me the main method looks much better because
we're breaking down the small steps and individual pieces of the program into named methods that have just a
little bit of code inside of each one, and to me that's always a better design that is going to be easier to maintain.
We're going to be talking more about design in the next module on Object-Oriented Programming.