Let's start this module by reviewing a few things that we know about methods.
Methods define behavior, they are our place where we can write code, and we can invoke a method to execute that code inside.
Every method has an access modifier, the default is private where the method is only available to other code
inside of the same class, but we can mark a method as internal to make it available to all the code inside of
the same project, or use the public keyword to make the method available everywhere.
Every method also has a return type, the method that we are looking at on the screen has a return type of
void, meaning the method doesn't return a value to the caller, it executes the code inside, but it doesn't
need a return statement to give anything back. Then we have the method name, and then 0 or more parameters,
which are listed in the parentheses after the name. This method takes one parameter, a numerical value of
type int, and the parameter is then a variable that is available throughout the rest of the method.
The method we are looking at takes this integer and passes it through to another method, the static GetBytes
method of the BitCoverter class. This BitConverter has a number of methods available to turn values into
bytes, and once we have the byte for our integer we will write out each byte to the console using some
special formatting symbols that know how to write out those values as hexadecimal numbers.
More on the formatting symbols in just a bit. Now here's a couple of new concepts about methods,
first there is a params keyword I want to show you in the demo.
The params keyword allows you to take a variable number of arguments because sometimes you might not know how
many parameters a method will need. Params is not typically something that you use on a regular basis,
but it's extremely useful in some scenarios. Another concept I want to introduce you to in the demo is the
concept of a method signature. You can think of a method signature as the unique identifier for a method.
The signature consists of the name of the method, as well as the number and the types of the parameters that the method takes.
The method signature allows the C# complier to distinguish between a method named WriteAsBytes that takes a
single int and another method with the same name, WriteAsBytes, but it takes a parameter of type string.
Those are two different methods, and I can have both methods in my class, and really I could have as many
methods named WriteAsBytes as I need, as long as the parameter lists are unique because parameter lists are
part of the signature. This is a feature in C# known as method overloading, and I do want to point out that
the return type of a method is not part of the method signature, let's take a closer look.
In this module we're going to continue to work with the GradeBook project that we created earlier in the
course, and if I run this project with Ctrl+F5 you can see we are outputting statistics, but without any
descriptive text for these numbers. So while you might be able to infer what is the average, the highest,
and the lowest grades, it would be nice if we added some text to make that more descriptive.
So each time I write out a result, I also want to write out a description of what that result is, and to do
that I'm going to create a helper method, a method that I can invoke from the main method of the program class.
Let's call this method WriteResult, I'll use the void keyword because this method doesn't need to return a
value, and this has to be a static method because I want to invoke this method from another static method,
and when you are inside a static member of a type you can only reach other static members of that same type,
so this has to be a static method that's called WriteResult. Every time I invoke this method I want to pass
in a description of the result that I'm going to write, and then the value of the result itself.
And inside of here let's just do a Console.WriteLine, I'll do that with the code snippet in Visual Studio CW,
press Tab and Tab, I want to write out the description, and let's just do some string concatenation to format
the output, so description plus a colon and a space, and then the result.
Let's try this out just with the average grade for right now, so I want to WriteResult, pass in the text
Average, and then the AverageGrade itself. Let's give that a quick run with Ctrl+F5, and that looks like the
type of output that I want, so I can change over some of the other values.
Before I do, let me take this WriteResult method, and make a copy of that with Ctrl+C, and then paste it with
Ctrl+V, and as soon as I do that Visual Studio will tell me that the C# complier sees an error, and the error
is that I cannot have two methods on a type with the same signature, so now I have two methods,
they're both called WriteResult, they both take two parameters of type string and float, so this is illegal,
but what happens if I change this version of WriteResult to take an integer value instead.
Now the C# complier sees two different methods, one that takes a string and an int, one that takes a string and a float.
So when I call write result here, which method will the C# complier choose, well generally speaking the C#
complier will choose the method that makes the most sense. So if I am invoking WriteResult, and I'm passing
a string and a floating point number, if the C# complier sees a method signature that matches those parameter
types exactly, that's the version of the overloaded method that it's going to invoke.
Now there are some subtleties and some crazy edge cases where sometimes the C# complier can choose a method
that you didn't expect, but for the most part the C# complier is going to do something sensible, so you can
see just based on the highlighting in Visual Studio that the version of WriteResult I'll be invoking is the
one that takes a string and a float. Now let's change over highest grade, and what I want to do is a
WriteResult, and I'll pass in the text Highest, and this time I want to take this highest grade and do an
explicit conversion to an integer, so this syntax in C# where you have a type name, or in this case the
keyword int, which maps to a type, the int 32 type, this is a type corrosion, some people would call this a
type cast, this is explicitly telling the C# complier I want to take this floating point number and convert
that value into an integer, and when you do this at runtime the floating point number will just be truncated.
If you actually wanted to do some rounding when you do the conversion there are some methods on the math
class that will allow you to round a number, but this time when I call WriteResult you can see based on the
highlighting the C# complier will choose the method that takes a string and an int.
So for the most part, the C# complier is just going to match up the parameters and their types so that everything works together.
And let's do this one more time, I want to WriteResult on the LowestGrade by passing in lowest, and now if I
run the program I have some nice output. And this is the essence of method overloading in C#.
Typically when you overload methods to take these different parameter types it's because you want to do
something different with those parameter types, in this case all we're really doing is just doing a
Console.WriteLine, but I want to show you the Console.WriteLine itself, it is an overloaded method.
So if I remove and retype the opening parenthesis that will bring up the IntellSense window that shows me all
of the different overloads of Console.WriteLine. Here's one that takes a bool, one that takes a character,
I can navigate through this using the arrow keys, here's a character array, a decimal value, a double value.
I want to show you a special version of WriteLine that is in here, the fifteenth overload of WriteLine,
this one takes a string and then an object array. Notice that object array has the params keywords in front.
That params keyword means that you can pass a variable number of arguments to this method, and a parameter to
a method that is marked with this params keyword, it's always the last parameter to a method because what the
C# complier will do as you start to pass parameters to this method, everything after the initial string,
the C# complier is just going to take all those parameters, package them up into an array, and pass them to
the method that you are invoking. So in other words, just as an experiment, if I used the params keyword
here, then my result would not be a single floating point number, instead it would be an array of floating
point number, and now what I can do is I can pass just a single value, but I could also continue to pass
values in here, so I could pass the lowest grade, and then a 2, and a 3, and a 4, and of course inside of
WriteResult what we'd have to do then is loop through this array, and display each result, this isn't really
what we want to do, I just want to demonstrate how you would use the params keyword, we just want a single
floating point result, so let me change this back, but what I do want to do is use this version of WriteLine
that takes what's known as a formatting string, and then a variable number of parameters because you'll see
this quite commonly in C# code. A formatting string looks like this, let's say I want to display the
description, and then a colon, and a space, and then the result.
One way to do that is with string concatenation, another way to do that is to use a formatting string like
so, and you can think of the pieces inside of the curly braces as placeholders, so I have placeholders 0 and
placeholder 1, and then the values that I pass here, that runtime will be placed into those placeholders.
In other words if I pass description and result, then at runtime instead of displaying curly brace 0 curly
brace, the runtime is going to go off looking for the first element in the array of parameters that I have
passed, so these two parameters, they are packaged up into an array, the first element would be description,
so description goes here. Now we have some literal text, which is the colon and the space, and then here's
another placeholder where I want array index 1 placed into here, so this will take the result and place it here.
If I run this program again, you'll see I still get the same output, which is quite often it's sometimes
easier to work with a formatting string than it is string concatenation because you can think of that
formatting string as a template, and it's sometimes a little bit easier to see the resulting string that
you're hoping to build. Now as the slide eluded to, there's also some special formatting characters that you
can add to these placeholders. I am not going to go into detail on all of the formatting options that are
available, you can go to your favorite search engine, and search for C# string formatting, and you'll find
lots of documentation because there are many formatting options.
There are all sorts of pneumonics to format DateTime values in a specific way, or to take this floating point
number and format it as a currency or in scientific notation. Here's an example, if I place a colon and a
F2, what I'm asking the runtime to do is to take my number, the result, and format it as a floating point
number with two digits after the decimal place, so you can see now instead of getting 85.166666, I get 85.17.
So this has even rounded the number for me. I can also place a C in here to format that value as a currency.
Notice that highest isn't formatted that way because when we displayed the highest grade we were displaying
it using this version of WriteResult that takes an integer. And now one more quick tip, if you're using
Visual Studio 2015 and the C# 6 complier, there's a new feature in C# version 6 called string interpolation,
it works like this. Instead of using these formatting strings, which can sometimes create trouble because
you forget that you really need two parameters in here, and you only pass one, a new feature of C# 6 string
interpolation allows you to place a dollar sign in front of the opening quote for this formatting string,
and instead of using numbers to index into an array, I can use the variable name directly, so this is a way
of saying please write out the description, whatever that string value is, and then the literal text colon
space, and now I want to write out the result, and I can still use a formatting string, so I want it to write
out as a floating point number with two digits after the decimal, and if we run this we're still getting the
output that we desire. So the key take-aways are that you can have overloaded methods in C#, that is methods
that have the same name, but different signatures, or the signature consists not only of the method name,
but also the number and the types of parameters, and the easy way to think about it is when you write code to
invoke WriteResult, will there be a way to distinguish between these two different methods, and in this case
since they both take two parameters, fortunately the last parameter has different types, so the C# complier
will choose the int method or the float method depending on the type of the value that you have to pass in.