Another type of member we've already been using is the field. Fields define the variables inside of a class,
so they define the state or the data that you want to hold as part of an object.
Previously we added a name field to our GradeBook class, and we made that field public, so anyone could go to
the GradeBook and change the name at anytime, but it is more common to make fields private and hide them,
so that no code outside of the class has access to the field. Data is something you typically want to
protect and validate, you don't want just anyone to be able to change the data inside of an object,
so the code on the screen is using a private field of type string, the name of the field is _name,
the underscore isn't required for private fields, that's just a naming convention that some developers use
for private fields, you don't have to use that convention, but this field is inside of a class named Animal,
and in the constructor for Animal we force someone to construct an animal by passing a name,
and the constructor saves the name in the private field, so it's available for the rest of the object to use.
Notice this field has a readonly keyword attached, that means the code inside of this class can only assign a
name in the constructor, or when the field is defined with a field initializer, so I could say private
readonly string _name = and some string value. If I try to set name to a new value in any other method other
than the constructor, the C# complier will give me an error for this class.
Now you might wonder how could I let code outside of my class get to the value of this field like the name,
do I have to write a method to return that value for other people to be able to read the name, and the answer
is no, that's where properties come in.
A property is similar to a field because it controls state and data associated with an object, but unlike a
field a property has a special syntax we can use to control what happens when someone reads the data or writes the data.
These are known as the get and set accessors, and these accessors can contain code, you can almost think of
them as methods, and we can do things like computations or validation.
In this code snippet we have a field called _name again, it is private, so I can only access the field
directly from code inside of the same class, but I also have a property called Name, and that's capitalized
because the naming guidelines for C# tell us to capitalize property names, as well as method names,
and I know this is a property because it has get and set accessors.
Inside of a get accessor I have some code, it's inside of curly braces just like the code inside of a method.
I can write as much code as I want inside of the get accessor, but ultimately I have to return a value,
and that value has to be of type string because that's the type of property that I'm inside, and this code is
just returning the same string that I already have in _name, but I could also return the name as uppercased,
or lowercased, or just the first three letters, whatever I want as long as I return a string.
Even more important here is the set accessor, inside of set, this is the code that will be invoked any time
someone tries to write a value into this name property, and whatever value someone is trying to write,
that will be passed to me implicitly through a variable called value.
You can think of this almost as a parameter to this set accessor if you're thinking of it as a method.
So I can take that value and store it directly under _name, but first do some validation to make sure that
someone's not trying to set name to null or to an empty string.
I want to make sure that the name actually has some characters, and that's a common use of set logic,
to validate an incoming value to make sure it meets some standards before you accept that value into your object.
There's another type of property in C# known as the auto-implemented property, this is a property that just
has the keywords get and set inside, there's semicolons after get and set, there's no curly braces or code,
and it's known as an auto-implemented property because behind the scenes the C# complier will automatically
create a field to store the value for this property, and it will automatically read that field during a get
operation, and write to that field during a set operation, but I never have to write that field or the code
explicitly, the C# complier will do that for me behind the scenes.
Let's take a closer look at this in code. Inside of our program let's open up the GradeBook, so I can remind
you about the public field that we added to this class earlier in the course, it's a field called Name,
and I have capitalized this member because it is a public member, and that's the typical convention in the C# program.
Inside of Program.cs I can make an assignment to that Name field just by saying book.Name = Scott's
GradeBook, so you can think of that as writing a reference into that field, a reference to a string that says
Scott's GradeBook, and I can read that value just by using the .operator and saying book.Name.
That will write out the name of the GradeBook when I run the program, and now I can see Scott's GradeBook.
Now let's change this over to being a property, and I'll start by implementing an auto-implemented property,
that's where I just have get and set with semicolons immediately after the keywords, there's no code
involved, but I have now changed this member of the GradeBook class from being a field to a property,
and you might be wondering what is the difference, well from a client's perspective, that is someone who's
using the Gradebook, there is no difference, I still say book.Name = to assign to that property,
that will call the setter, and I still use book.Name to retrieve the value of that property, and read the
property, that will call the getter, and behind the scenes the C# complier has automatically created a
backing field for this property, that's what we would call the field behind a property that actually stores the value.
So this change hasn't made a huge difference in my code, but I will tell you there are some parts to the .NET
Framework and other frameworks that treat properties and fields differently, specifically if you're doing
serialization, that is if you're taking an object, and you're serializing it into XML, or JSON, or saving it
to a database, there are some frameworks that only look at properties when they do the serialization,
they do not look at fields by default. There are also data-binding features in the .NET Framework,
these are features where you assign an object to some part of your user interface, and the data-binding
features will automatically move data from an object onto the screen, and some of these data-binding features
will only move properties, they won't look at fields, so again there can be a very subtle difference between
fields and properties, and I would say in general in you're going to make the member publically available,
we typically do that through a property instead of a field. In other words I will keep the grades field as a
field and keep that private, I only want to be able to change grades inside of this class, but names,
since I'm making that publically available, I will make that a property, and I will make it a capitalized
member of the type, although it is perfectly legal to have private properties or internal properties,
but I would say you just don't see them that often. But what if we wanted to protect against this situation,
what if we wanted to protect against someone saying book.Name = an empty string, or book.Name = null,
so null is a keyword in C#, and as we talked about before a field or a variable that holds a null value,
it doesn't point to anything, it doesn't reference anything, there's no object, or there's no string there
now to interact with, and currently if I run the program, if I try to Console.WriteLine that null value it
just comes out as blank. I want to prevent that, and that means I won't be able to use an auto-implemented
property, I'm going to need to add some logic to my setter to perform some validation, and as soon as I start
to add code to the setter then I either need to get rid of my getter or also add code to the getter,
and because I'm not using an auto-implemented property anymore I'm going to need to create a field explicitly
that will be able to hold that string value, so I will create a private field called _name, and when someone
wants to read the name property I'll just return name, but again I could do anything that I wanted to in here.
I could return a new string that was uppercased, or lowercased, or a sub string, I'll just return _name,
and when someone's trying to write to this property I want to check to see if the string is null or empty,
so I can write String.IsNullOrEmpty, that is a static method on the string class.
I will pass in value, which is the implicit variable that I have inside of a setter that will contain the
value that someone is trying to write into my property, and then IsNullOrEmpty will return true is value IsNullOrEmpty.
If I put an exclamation point here, that is a logical not operation that would turn that true into a false,
so I'm saying if the string is not null or empty only then will I assign that value into the name,
otherwise I will ignore this value. What I'd really like to do is create an error condition if someone gives
me an empty name, that way I can let the caller know that they did something wrong, but we'll talk about
error conditions like that more in the next module when we talk about exceptions.
For right now I just want to show you when I run the program, this assignment Book.Name = null, we should be
ignoring that value, we'll stick with Scott's GradeBook, and that's the real power of properties.
You can write logic inside of a get accessor and a set accessor.
The get accessor can perform computations, or just retrieve some field value, and return it, the set accessor
can perform validations, and it can protect the internal state of your object, and make sure that someone
isn't giving you a value that you don't want. So properties are really all about state, methods are still
all about behavior, and next let's turn our attention to one more type of member that we can add to a type.