Another type of member that you can have in a class is an event.
To understand events we need to delve into some new concepts in C# and .NET, but before we do let me give you
a high-level overview of why events are useful. Many times in software development we need to interact with
or keep track of components that do interesting things at unpredictable times.
For example, a button on a screen is a component that we want to keep track of, and we want to know when a
user clicks on this button. We don't know exactly when the user will click on the button, but we do need to
be notified because when the user does click we typically need to then execute some code.
Sometimes we need to save data to a file or read data from a database, and this isn't just about components
on the screen like a button. We might need to also keep track of a directory on the hard drive and be
notified when a user places a new file on that directory, or when a timer expires because I want to execute
some code every 60 seconds, and refresh some data, like refreshing stock quotes.
All these are examples of when events are useful. Events allow an object, like an object that represents a
button, events allow that object to announce to anyone who is listening that something interesting happened,
like when the user clicks on that button. We call the announcement an event, and we say that the button publishes this event.
The code that is interested in the click event is code that subscribes to the event.
You can have multiple subscribers listening to a single click event, so that when the user clicks a button 0
or more independent pieces of code will execute. One piece of code might save data to a file,
another piece might change the color of the screen, another piece might log information to a database,
those are three independent pieces of code all executing off of the same event, and the beauty of events is
that the button object itself, it doesn't need to keep track of who is subscribing, and the subscribers don't
need to know about each other. This is all done through the magic of delegates in C#, so in order to
understand events we really need to understand delegates first.