Imagine that you want to declare a variable that references a method, so not a variable to hold an integer,
or point to a string, or point to any class object, you want to declare a variable, and point the variable to
a method, that means you'll have a variable that encapsulates executable code, and you can invoke the
variable just like you would invoke a method by using parentheses and optionally passing some arguments along.
In order for this to work you'll need to create a delegate type, so a delegate is a type just like we used
the class keyword to create a type, or the struct keyword to create a type, there is a delegate keyword in
the C# language, and that keyword will allow me to create a type that is dedicated to referencing methods,
and that means the type definition for a delegate looks much different than a class definition.
The type definition looks almost like a method definition, the type definition describes the methods that I want to call.
In this code snippet I'm creating a delegate called Writer. I know this is a delegate because I can see the
delegate keyword, and a variable of this type will point to a method that returns void and takes a string parameter.
There's no curly braces here, I'm not defining a method with executable code, I just end the statement with a semicolon.
I am defining a type that I can use to create variables, and point those variables to methods that have this
same signature and same return type. Again the name of this type is Writer.
Now imagine I have a class called Logger. I can instantiate a Logger, and once I have a Logger I can invoke
a WriteMessage method, and have the Logger do something interesting like print a message to the screen.
I can also write a bit of code that instantiates a Logger and then instantiates a delegate that references
the WriteMessage method itself of the Logger object. That's what this bit of code here is doing.
Notice I'm not invoking logger.WriteMessage, there are no parentheses after WriteMessage, this code is
literally creating a new instance of a delegate and passing the WriteMessage method to this writer delegate.
That delegate is saved into a variable named Writer, and I can now invoke logger.WriteMessage just by
invoking this variable, all I need to do is apply parentheses to the variable and pass the string parameter
that I want the Logger to use. Now depending on what programming background you have, this information might
be a bit foreign. If you come from a C or C++ background you can think of a delegate as a way of creating a
type save function pointer, and if you come from any functional language like JavaScript, the idea of
having a variable that points to a function, that's not new, it's just going to be the C# syntax and all the
type checking that you'll need to get used to because the C# complier is very picky about the methods that I
can point to with a delegate. Like in this example, a writer delegate will only work with methods that
return void and take a single string parameter. Notice the name of the method doesn't matter, I can have the
delegate called Writer, and reference a method called WriteMessage, or any other name as long as that method
returns void and takes a string. Let's take a look at this in Visual Studio.
Back inside of the GradeBook let's look at a scenario where something else in the application needs to know
when the name of the GradeBook is changing. Maybe that something else is a data-binding framework that needs
to update the screen with the new GradeBook name whenever the name changes.
We don't know, we just know that the only place in the entire application that knows exactly when the
GradeBook name is changing is the code that is inside of the setter for the name property itself.
If from inside of here I could announce somehow that the name is changing and invoke some other code,
that would satisfy my requirements that I need to call something else in the application when the name
changes, but I don't know what. That's the perfect scenario for delegates because delegates essentially
allow you to have a variable that points to a method, and because it's a variable it can point to different
methods it can be assigned to, and that's what I need inside of my setter, I need to know when the name is
changing, perhaps I could have an additional if check here to say if _name is not equal to the incoming
value, so I know for a fact that the name is changing, that I want to be able to invoke some arbitrary code.
Let's say I have a delegate called NameChanged. I want to be able to invoke that, perhaps I pass in the
existing name, and the new value that will be assigned to the name, and that will fulfill my responsibility
to the outside world that I've made this announcement, my name is changing.
In order to pull this off I'm going to need a delegate, so let me right-click on the GradeBook project,
and I'm going to say Add, Class even though what I really want is a delegate, this is the easiest way to get
a .cs file into the project. I will call this NameChangedDelegate, and press Add.
Visual Studio will assume I want something with a .cs extension, and no, I don't want a class, and I don't
want the curly braces. What I do want is a new type, a public type that I'll create with delegate, and now I
need to describe the types of methods that this can invoke. I don't care about the return value from this
method, all I know is it's going to need to take two string values, so let me create this delegate by saying
the method will return void, and the method will take two string parameters, let's call them existingName and newName.
Just remember that the names of these parameters are arbitrary.
When the C# complier is checking to make sure this delegate points to the proper method it doesn't check the
parameter names to make sure they match, it's only going to check the type, so a method that returns void and
takes two strings, that's the type of method that I can point this delegate to.
And so with this delegate back in the GradeBook I can now create a public field using that delegate type,
so public NameChangedDelegate, let's call it NameChanged, and I now have a public member that other areas of
the application can walk up, and assign to this delegate, and give it the code that needs to be invoked out
there somewhere in the outside world. All I need to do in my GradeBook is just invoke that delegate at the
appropriate time when the name has changed. Now just so we get some interesting output let's initialize
_name to something inside of the constructor for the GradeBook just so there is always some value there.
Let's just use the text Empty, and now what I want to do back in my program is take advantage of this new
feature to execute arbitrary code when the name of the GradeBook changes.
So back in Program.cs at some point after I create the book I want to be able to say book.NameChanged = a new
instance of the NameChangedDelegate, and then pass in a method that can be invoked.
I currently don't have a method that returns void and takes two strings, so before we finish that line of
code, let's write something. This will have to be a static method so that I can reach it from the main method.
It has to be a method that returns void. I can call it anything I want, let's call it OnNameChanged,
and I just have to take two string parameters, the names don't matter, but I think existingName and newName,
those are pretty good parameter names, so we will stick with those, and when this method is invoked I want to
write out some information. Let's use some string interpolation, and say Grade book changing name from
existingName to newName, and that should be everything that I need, so let me take this method name,
and copy it, and I should be able to paste it here, and the delegate will be happy and say ah, you want me to
call OnNameChanged whenever someone invokes this delegate. Let's try it, Ctrl+F5 to run, and I can see
Grade book changing name from Empty to Scott's Grade Book, and this should happen anytime the name changes,
so I should be able to say book.Name = Scott's Grade Book, and let's say book.Name = just Grade Book.
We should see that method fire twice, and it does. It goes from Empty to Scott's Grade Book and then Scott's
to just Grade Book, and this is the type of situation where you want to use a delegate, so going back to the
UI example that we talked about earlier, let's say you're writing your class that's going to have a button
associated with it because it's a part of a user interface, and your class, the code inside of it will know
when the button is clicked, but how can your class announce to the rest of the world when that button is
clicked because chances are it might not be just you that is interested in that button click, you might need
to tell other pieces of the application when the button is clicked.
How can you do that? Ultimately it's done with events that build on top of delegates, and right now we're
just focusing on the delegate part. So let me show you a few other things that are interesting about delegates.
Let's come back to Program.cs, and let me create a copy of OnNameChanged, and I'm going to paste it,
and we know now that will create a complier error because we have two methods with the exact same signature,
but I will change the second one to be OnNameChanged2, and let's do something simple inside of here like
write out three asterix, and now back up at the top, what happens when if I say book.NameChanged = this new
NameChangedDelegate OnNameChanged, and then right after that line of code I assign again with OnNameChanged2.
Well if I run the program what we'll see is that we're only outputting asterixs now, and that's because I've
effectively overwritten the information inside of that delegate that would allow me to call OnNameChanged,
I've overwritten that delegate, I'm now calling OnNameChanged2 only.
However the interesting thing about delegates in C# is they can reference multiple methods, we call them
MutlicastDelegates because when I invoke a delegate that might call one method, but a delegate can also hold
references to multiple methods, so invoking NameChanged might actually call 10 different methods because
there might be 10 different pieces of the application that are interested in knowing when the name of a
GradeBook has changed, and the way I can get that to work is instead of doing an assignment I can use the += operation.
You might remember += from some of the mathematical operations we did with integers.
I can say some variable += 3, an integer variable, and that will take whatever is in that integer variable,
and add 3 to it, it's like saying x = x+3. This is the same concept, I'm saying take whatever is in
NameChanged, and add this additional delegate, and then add this additional delegate, so that now when I run
the program each time the name changes, not only do I invoke OnNameChanged, but I also invoke OnNameChanged2,
and just so you know there's also a -= operation to remove a reference to a method, that would effectively be
a way of saying I don't care about the NameChanged operation anymore, please remove me from your list of
methods that you call, but this capability of being able to invoke multiple methods, this is ideal again for
situations like building a UI component, or there might be multiple people, or multiple components that are
interested in that button click event, and although I could do that with delegates, delegates don't quite
offer enough encapsulation because someone can always walk up to book.NameChanged, and say I'm going to set
this to null, which is empty it out, and that effectively overwrites all the previous delegates that were in
there, and that's not something that I want to happen if I want different areas of the application to be able
to independently subscribe to this event that the GradeBook name is changing.
I want to prevent lines of code like this somehow, and that's exactly what I can do by using events instead
of delegates, let's look at that next.