Once you have a handle on how delegates work, it's very easy to
understand events because events are based on and use delegates.
The only thing I need to do to make NameChanged a proper event is to add the C# keyword here event,
and now there is no code that I need to change inside of the GradeBook because events are based on delegates,
and I can still invoke NameChanged. The C# complier will still check to make sure that I pass along two
parameters, both of type string, and there's nothing that has to change inside of the GradeBook.
The reason that events are preferred to just exposing delegates is because of the error that we see inside of Program.cs.
The error is that NameChanged can only appear on the left-hand side of += or -=.
That means from outside of the GradeBook the only thing that other pieces of code can do is add a subscriber
to event, or remove a subscriber to this event, and it's no longer possible to do an assignment, and wipe out
everything that was inside, wipe out all the other subscriptions.
This is what we want for events because we want independent pieces of code being able to subscribe and
unsubscribe, and not interfere with others, so this line of code is now an error, I will remove that line of
code, and just show you that I can use += as many times as I want, I can even wire up the same method twice.
Now you can see every time the name changes I get two sets of asterix, and I will also point out now that the
C# complier is pretty intelligent when it comes to using Events and delegates, and the syntax that I'm
currently using to wire up a subscriber for that event is a little bit verbose.
I can actually remove new NameChangedDelegate, I can remove that from all three lines of code, and then once
I get rid of the parentheses at the end I will still have legal C# code, because the C# complier is smart
enough to look at NameChanged, and the method that I'm trying to add as a subscriber, and it can figure out
that those two things are compatible, and it will just automatically create that delegate instance for me
behind the scenes, I don't have to explicitly say new and then the name of some delegate.
So this code is a little bit easier on the eyes, and just as a quick quiz, what happens if I add another line
of code here with a -= operation, so now I'm subscribing OnNameChanged2 twice, and then unsubscribing once.
The question is will -= wipe out all of the subscriptions for OnNameChanged2 or just one of them, and if I
run the program we'll see I now have just one set of asterix, so OnNameChanged2 was subscribed twice,
removed once, and then that result was one subscription, therefore that method fires once every time the name changes.
Now I also want to point out that we're doing something unconventional with our event, and that is that we're
passing two string parameters along with this event. There is a convention in .NET, it's not a convention
that you have to follow, but it's a convention that 99.9% of all events in the .NET Framework follow.
It's a convention where an event always passes along two parameters, the first parameter is going to be the
sender of the event, in other words if the GradeBook is announcing that the name has changed, it's going to
send itself as the first parameter, and then the second parameter always contains all of the arguments or all
of the needed information about that event, which means I'm going to need to build a custom class to put
together the existing name and the new name into a single object so I can pass that object along as the arguments.
Let's make this change. I'm going to go to the GradeBook project, and add another class, I'll call this
class NameChangedEventArgs, which is another convention when you are working with events.
The parameter that passes along the argument for the event, the name of its type will always end with the words EventArgs.
So now I have my class, let me add the public keyword here to make this a public class, and now I need
properties for the existing name and the new name. The easiest way to add a property when you're using
Visual Studio is to use a code snippet p, r, o, p, I'll just type that and press Tab twice, now I can fill in
the type for my property, and then Tab twice over to the name, and fill out the name of my property,
and Visual Studio will give me an auto-implemented property. Let me go to the next line of code and p, r, o,
p again, this time I want the NewName property to be here. So this will give me my EventArgs class,
and something that we'll talk about in the Object Oriented Programming module of this course is how a class
can inherent from another class. If you haven't worked with inheritance before then you can just wait till
we get to that module for me to explain this in more detail, but in .NET anything that's going to pass along
arguments inside of an event, it should derive or inherent from an EventArgs base class that the .NET Framework provides.
That's what this syntax is doing, it's specifying an inheritance relationship where NameChangedEventArgs derives from EventArgs.
Again, more on inheritance later. Now I want to change over my delegate so it's not taking two string parameters any longer.
Instead, it needs to take the sender of this event, and then the NameChangedEventArgs, an object of that type.
Why am I specifying sender as an object? Object is another one of those topics that we'll talk a little more
about when we talk about object-oriented programming, but this is another convention in .NET around events,
and when I have a parameter typed in as an object, that means I can pass anything as a parameter here.
I can pass an integer value, or a string, or a GradeBook instance, and if the GradeBook is the sender of this
event, GradeBook is what I want to pass here, but I will type it as object because that's a common convention.
Now that I've changed the delegate around I will have some complier errors both in Program.cs and in GradeBook.cs.
In GradeBook.cs I need to pass EventArgs and the sender here instead of two strings.
So first let's create an instance of NameChangedEventArgs, I will just call it args, and initialize a new
instance, and say that the ExistingName equals the value that I currently have in _name, and the NewName that
will equal the incoming value, and now when I invoke NameChanged, I should really pass along myself and then these arguments.
How do I pass along myself? Well inside of every non-static method in a C# class or struct, there is an
implicit variable called this, and this will reference the object that I'm inside of, so this will reference
the GradeBook object that we're currently operating on. I just need to pass along this and args, and just to
show you if I type this., here you can see all of the members of the GradeBook, so there's _Name,
there's the property name, there's the private field grades, I can see private fields through this because
I'm using code that is inside of the same class, so this is a variable that you can use anywhere in your C#
code inside of an instance member if you need to refer to yourself, or pass yourself along as another
parameter, and now I will need to change Program.cs because delegates are very type safe, and now the C#
complier sees that I'm using these methods that no longer take the parameters that the delegate is
describing, so I wrote these methods as taking two strings, and now this delegate is trying to pass an object
and a NameChangedEventArgs, so I'm going to need to change these around.
Let's actually get rid of OnNameChanged2 all together, that makes this a little less work, and up here
OnNameChanged, I will change this around so that it can take a sender parameter, and then an instance of
NameChangedEventArgs, and down here I will just need to change these to use args.ExistingName,
and args.NewName, then let's remove the subscription to OnNameChanged2, that method no longer exists,
run the GradeBook, I can still see it's behaving correctly, and this is the magic of events in .NET.
Not all programming environments use events, but they are quite common if you're doing some sort of desktop
program, that is a C# application that runs under Windows or runs on a mobile phone.
It's quite common that your user interface elements will have events to let your code know when something
was clicked on or if something was hovered over, and now you'll know that you can subscribe to those events
using += and a method that accepts the parameters that event will raise.