In this module we looked at the different members that you can add to a class.
We looked at fields and properties, which can hold an exposed state.
We also looked at methods again, this time seeing how you can overload methods by writing multiple methods
with the same name, but different signatures. Remember the signature is defined not only by the name of the
method, but also the types and the number of parameters to that method.
And finally we looked at events, which allow subscribers to listen for interesting things that might happen in an object.
We saw how events are based on delegates, which are useful in other places in .NET programming too.
If you want more information on events and delegates I do spend some time on them in both my C# Generics
course and my Linq Fundamentals course. The whole goal of seeing fields, properties, methods, constructors,
and events all together is to know what tools are available when you want to build an abstraction in C#.
In this case we've built a GradeBook that encapsulates the behavior of the GradeBook.
It can computer statistics and raise events when important state changes happen.
We'll continue seeing how to build abstractions when we talk about object-oriented programming, but first we
will in the next module look at flow control in C#, which is how to branch, and loop, and both create,
and catch runtime errors.